  <appendix id="svn-ap-c">
    <title>Troubleshooting</title>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ======================== SECTION 1 ============================== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn-ap-c-sect-1">
      <title>Common Problems</title>

      <para>There are a number of problems you may run into in the
        course of installing and using Subversion.  Some of these will
        be resolved once you get a better idea of how Subversion does
        things, while others are caused because you're used to the way
        that other version control systems work.  Still other problems
        might be unsolvable due to bugs in some of the operating
        systems that Subversion runs on (considering the wide array of
        OS'es that Subversion runs on, it's amazing that we don't
        encounter many more of these).</para>

      <para>The following list has been compiled over the course of
        several years of Subversion usage, and they cover just about
        every frequently occurring problem that you'll see in
        Subversion&mdash;from building, to installing, to using
        Subversion.  If you can't find the problem you're having here,
        or you've tried everything we recommend with no success, send
        mail to <address>users@subversion.tigris.org</address> with a
        detailed description of the problem you're having
        <footnote><para>Remember that the amount of detail you provide
        about your setup and your problem is directly proportional to
        the likelihood of getting an answer from the mailing list.
        You're encouraged to include everything short of what you had
        for breakfast and your mother's maiden name.  </para>
        </footnote> </para>
      
      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Problems Using Subversion</title>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>Every time I try to access my repository,
            <command>svn</command> just hangs.</para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>Every time I try to run <command>svn</command>, it
            says my working copy is locked.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>I'm getting errors finding or opening a repository,
            but I know my repository URL is correct.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>I'm running Subversion under Windows and I can create
            a repository fine, but I get errors trying to import or
            check out from it.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>I'm having trouble doing write operations to a
            Subversion repository over a network.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Under Windows XP, the Subversion server sometimes
            seems to send out corrupted data.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>What is the best method of doing a network trace of
            the conversation between a Subversion client and
            server?</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <itemizedlist>
        <title>Problems Building Subversion</title>

        <listitem>
          <para>I just built the distribution binary, and when I try
            to check out Subversion, I get an error about an
            <quote>Unrecognized URL scheme.</quote></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>When I run <command>configure</command>, I get errors
            like <literal>subs-1.sed line 38: Unterminated `s'
            command</literal>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>I'm having trouble building Subversion under Windows
          with MSVC++ 6.0.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      
      <sect2 id="svn-ap-c-sect-1.2">
        <title>Problems Using Subversion</title>

      <sect3 id="svn-ap-c-sect-1.2.1">
          <title>Every time I try to access my repository, my
          Subversion client just hangs.</title>

          <para>Subversion uses Berkeley DB, which keeps your data in
            a series of database files.  Berkeley DB is journaling
            system, meaning that it logs every action it is about to
            perform before it actually performs the action. If your
            client is interrupted while in the process of talking to
            the database, then a lockfile is left behind in the
            database, along with a logfile describing the unfinished
            actions.</para>

          <para>Any other client that attempts to access the database
            will just hang, waiting for the lockfile to disappear. To
            awaken your repository, you need to tell Berkeley DB to
            either finish the work, or rewind the database to a
            previous state that is known to be consistent.  To do
            this, run the following command from the machine that
            contains your Subversion Repository:</para>

          <screen>          
$ svnadmin recover /path/to/repos
          </screen>

          <para>Be sure that you disable all access to the repository
            before doing this (by shutting down httpd or
            svnserve). Make sure you run this command as the user that
            owns and manages the database, and not as root, else it
            will leave root-owned files in the
            <filename>db/</filename> directory which cannot be opened
            by the non-root user that manages the database, which is
            typically either you or your Apache httpd process.</para>

        </sect3>


        <sect3 id="svn-ap-c-sect-1.2.2">
          <title>Every time I try to run <command>svn</command>, it
            says my working copy is locked.</title>

          <para>Subversion's working copy, just like Berkeley DB, uses
            a journaling mechanism to perform all actions. That is, it
            logs everything it is about to do before it does so. If
            <command>svn</command> is interrupted while performing an
            action, then one or more lockfiles are left behind, along
            with logfiles describing then unfinished
            actions. (<command>svn status</command> will show an
            <literal>L</literal> next to locked directories).</para>

          <para>Any other process that attempts to access the working
            copy will fail when it sees the locks. To awaken your
            working copy, you need to tell the svn client to finish
            the work.  To fix this, run this command from the top of
            your working copy:</para>

          <screen>
$ svn cleanup working-copy
          </screen>

        </sect3>


        <sect3 id="svn-ap-c-sect-1.2.3">
          <title>I'm getting errors finding or opening a repository,
            but I know my repository URL is correct.</title>

          <para>See <xref linkend="svn-ap-c-sect-1.2.1"/>.</para>

        </sect3>


        <sect3 id="svn-ap-c-sect-1.2.4">
          <title>I'm running Subversion under Windows and I can create
            a repository fine, but I get errors trying to import or
            check out from it.</title>

          <para>If the error looks something like:</para>

          <screen>
svn_error: #21085 : 
  svn_ra_local__split_URL: Unable to find valid repository
          </screen>

          <para>Then the problem is that Subversion doesn't handle
          file URLs that have a drive specification. Try changing to
          that drive then doing an import without the drive spec. For
          example:</para>

          <screen>
d: 
svn import file:///some/path/to/repos/on/d/drive e:\file\to\be\imported
          </screen>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="svn-ap-c-sect-1.2.5">
          <title>I'm having trouble doing write operations to a
            Subversion repository over a network</title>
          
          <para>If import works fine over local access:</para>
          
          <screen>
$ mkdir test
$ touch test/testfile
$ svn import file:///var/svn/test test test -m "Initial import"
Adding         test/testfile
Transmitting file data .
Committed revision 1.
          </screen>

          <para>But not from a remote host:</para>

          <screen>
$ svn import http://svn.red-bean.com/test testfile -m "import"
harry's password: xxxxxxx

svn_error: #21110 : 

The specified activity does not exist.
          </screen>

          <para>We've seen this when the
            <filename>REPOS/dav/</filename> directory is not writable
            by the httpd process. Check the permissions to ensure that
            Apache httpd can write to the <filename>dav/</filename>
            directory (and to the corresponding
            <filename>db/</filename> directory, of course).</para>

        </sect3>


        <sect3 id="svn-ap-c-sect-1.2.6">
          <title>Under Windows XP, the Subversion server sometimes
            seems to send out corrupted data.</title>

          <para>You need to install Window XP Service Pack 1.  You can
            get all sorts of information about that Service Pack at
            <systemitem
            class="url">http://support.microsoft.com/default.aspx?scid=kb;EN-US;q317949</systemitem>
            for details.</para>
        </sect3>


        <sect3 id="svn-ap-c-sect-1.2.7">
          <title>What is the best method of doing a network trace of
            the conversation between a Subversion client and
            server?</title>

          <para>Use Ethereal to eavesdrop on the conversation:</para>

          <note>
            <para>The following instructions are specific to the
              graphical version of Ethereal, and may not apply to the
              commandline version (whose binary is usually named
              tethereal).</para>
          </note>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Pull down the Capture menu, and choose
              Start.</para>
            </listitem>
            
            <listitem>
              <para>Type port 80 for Filter, and turn off promiscuous
                mode.</para>
            </listitem>
            
            <listitem>
              <para>Run your Subversion client.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Hit Stop. Now you have a capture. It looks like a
                huge list of lines.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Click on the Protocol column to sort.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Then, click on the first relevant TCP line to
              select it.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Right click, and choose Follow TCP Stream. You'll
                be presented with the request/response pairs of the
                Subversion client's HTTP conversion.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>Alternatively, you may set the http-debug parameter in
            the server's configuration file to cause neon's debugging
            output to appear when you run the svn client. The numeric
            value of neon-debug is a combination of the
            <literal>NE_DBG_*</literal> values in the header file
            <filename>ne_utils.h</filename>. Setting
            <literal>http-debug</literal> to 130
            (i.e. <literal>NE_DBG_HTTP + NE_DBG_HTTPBODY</literal>)
            will cause the HTTP data to be shown.</para>

          <para>You may well want to disable compression when doing a
            network trace, see the compression parameter in the config
            configuration file.</para>
        </sect3>

      </sect2>


      <sect2 id="svn-ap-c-sect-1.3">
        <title>Problems Building Subversion</title>

        <sect3 id="svn-ap-c-sect-1.3.1">
          <title>I just built the distribution binary, and when I try
            to check out Subversion, I get an error about an
            <quote>Unrecognized URL scheme</quote></title>


          <para>Subversion uses a plugin system to allow access to
            repositories. Currently there are three of these plugins:
            <literal>ra_local</literal> allows access to a local
            repository, <literal>ra_dav</literal> which allows access
            to a repository via WebDAV, and <literal>ra_svn</literal>
            allows local or remote access via the svnserve
            server. When you attempt to perform an operation in
            Subversion, the client tries to dynamically load a plugin
            based on the URL scheme. A <literal>file://</literal> URL
            will try to load <literal>ra_local</literal>, an
            <literal>http://</literal> URL will try to load ra_dav,
            and so on.</para>

          <para>The error you are seeing means that the dynamic
            linker/loader can't find the plugins to load. This
            normally happens when you build Subversion with shared
            libraries, then attempt to run it without first running
            <literal>make install'</literal> Another possible cause is
            that you ran make install, but the libraries were
            installed in a location that the dynamic linker/loader
            doesn't recognize. Under Linux, you can allow the
            linker/loader to find the libraries by adding the library
            directory to <filename>/etc/ld.so.conf</filename> and
            running <command>ldconfig</command>. If you don't wish to
            do this, or you don't have root access, you can also
            specify the library directory in the
            <literal>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</literal> environment
            variable.</para>
        </sect3>


        <sect3 id="svn-ap-c-sect-1.3.2">
          <title>When I run <command>configure</command>, I get errors
            like <literal>subs-1.sed line 38: Unterminated `s'
            command</literal></title>

          <para>You probably have old copies of
            <filename>/usr/local/bin/apr-config</filename> and
            <filename>/usr/local/bin/apu-config</filename> on your
            system. Remove them, make sure the
            <filename>apr/</filename> and
            <filename>apr-util/</filename> that you're building with
            are completely up-to-date, and try again.</para>
        </sect3>


        <sect3 id="svn-ap-c-sect-1.3.3">
          <title>I'm having trouble building Subversion under Windows
          with MSVC++ 6.0.</title>

          <para>You need to get the latest platform SDK. The one that
            ships with VCa++ 6.0 is not recent enough.</para>

        </sect3>

      </sect2>

    </sect1>

</appendix>

<!--
local variables: 
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "appendix")
end:
-->
