<chapter id="svn-ch-1">

  <title>Introduction</title>

  <simplesect>
    <para>Version control is the art of managing changes to
      information.  It has long been a critical tool to programmers,
      who typically spend their time making small changes to software
      and then undoing those changes the next day.  Imagine a team of
      these programmers working concurrently, and you can see why a
      good version control system is needed to manage the potential
      chaos.</para>
  </simplesect>


  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ======================== SECTION 1 ============================== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn-ch-1-sect-1">

    <title>What is Subversion?</title>
      
    <para>Subversion is a free/open-source version control system.
      That is, Subversion manages files and directories over time.
      The tree of files are placed into a central
      <firstterm>repository</firstterm>.  The repository is much like
      an ordinary file server, except that it remembers every change
      ever made to your files and directories.  This allows you to
      recover older versions of your tree, or examine the history of
      how your data changed.  In this regard, many people think of a
      version control system as a sort of ``time machine.''</para>
    
    <!-- ### something about subversion facilitating communication
    between developers?? -->

    <para>Some version control systems are also software configuration
      management (SCM) systems.  These systems are specifically
      tailored to manage trees of source code, and have many features
      that are specific to software development (such as natively
      understanding programming languages).  Subversion, however, is
      not one of these systems; it is a general system that can be
      used to manage <emphasis>any</emphasis> sort of collection of
      files, including source code.</para>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ======================== SECTION 2 ============================== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn-ch-1-sect-2">

    <title>Subversion's History</title>

    <para>In 1995, Karl Fogel and Jim Blandy founded Cyclic Software,
      a company for commercially supporting and improving the
      Concurrent Versions Sysetm (CVS).  Cyclic made the first public
      release of a network-enabled CVS (contributed by Cygnus
      software.)  In 1999, Karl Fogel published a book about CVS and
      the open-source development model it enables.  Karl and Jim had
      long talked about writing a replacement for CVS; Jim had even
      drafted a new, theoretical repository design, and had come up
      with a good project name.  Finally, in February of 2000, Brian
      Behlendorf of CollabNet (http://www.collab.net) offered Karl a
      full-time job to write a CVS replacement.  Karl gathered a team
      together and work began in May.  Because Subversion was
      developed openly under a free license, it quickly attracted a
      community of developers.</para>

    <para>The original design team settled on two simple goals.
      First, it was decided that Subversion should be a functional
      replacement for CVS.  That is, it should match CVS's features,
      preserve the same development model, but still fix the most
      obvious flaws.  Second, Subversion should be written such that
      any CVS user can start using it with little effort.</para>

    <para>After fourteen months of coding, Subversion became
      "self-hosting" on August 31, 2001.  That is, Subversion
      developers stopped using CVS to manage Subversion's own source
      code and started using Subversion instead.</para>

    <para>While CollabNet is credited with initiating and funding a
      very large chunk of the work (it pays the salaries of a few
      full-time Subversion developers), the project is still a typical
      open-source project, governed by the usual meritocratic rules.
      CollabNet owns the copyright on the code, but that copyright is
      an Apache/BSD-style license which is fully compliant with the
      Debian Free Software Guidelines. In other words, anyone is free
      to download, modify, and redistribute Subversion as he pleases;
      no permission from CollabNet or anyone else is required.</para>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ======================== SECTION 3 ============================== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn-ch-1-sect-3">

    <title>Subversion's Features</title>

    <para>How does Subversion improve upon CVS's design?  Here's a
      short list to whet your appetite.  If you're not familiar with
      CVS, you may not understand all of these features.  Fear not:
      Chapter 2 will provide you with a gentle introduction to version
      control.</para>

    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Directory versioning</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The Subversion repository doesn't only track the
            history of individual files; instead, it implements a
            <quote>virtual</quote> versioned filesystem that tracks
            changes to trees over time.  Files
            <emphasis>and</emphasis> directories are versioned.  As a
            result, there are real client-side <command>move</command>
            and <command>copy</command> commands that operate on files
            and directories.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Atomic commits</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A commit either goes into the repository completely,
            or not all.  This allows developers to commit changes as
            logical <quote>changesets</quote>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Versioned metadata</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Each file and directory has an invisible set of
            <quote>properties</quote> attached.  You can invent and
            store any arbitrary key/value pairs you wish.  Properties
            are versioned over time, just like file contents.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Advanced network layer</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The Subversion network server is the Apache web
            server, and the Subversion client and server speak the
            WebDAV protocol to one another, which is an extension of
            HTTP.  This gives Subversion a big advantage in stability
            and interoperability, and provides various key features
            for free: authentication, authorization, wire compression,
            and repository browsing, for example. <!-- mention
            svnserve here someday -->
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Better binary handling</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Subversion expresses file differences using a binary
            diffing algorithm, which works equally well on both text
            and binary files.  Text and binary files are stored
            equally compressed in the repository, and differences are
            transmitted in both directions across the network.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Efficient branching and tagging</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            There's no need for branching/tagging to proportional to
            project size.  Subversion creates branches and tags by
            simply copying the project, using a mechanism similar to a
            hard-link.  Thus the operations take only a very small,
            constant amount of time.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Hackability</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Subversion has no historical baggage; it is
            implemented a collection of shared C libraries with
            well-defined APIs.  This makes Subversion extremely
            maintainable and usable by other applications and
            languages.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

  </sect1>


  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ======================== SECTION 4 ============================== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn-ch-1-sect-4">

    <title>Subversion's components</title>

    


  </sect1>


  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ======================== SECTION 5 ============================== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn-ch-1-sect-5">

    <title>How to get Subversion</title>

    <para>### TODO Write this.  List URLs, RPMs, etc.</para>

  </sect1>

</chapter>

<!--
local variables: 
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->
