<!-- This chapter is slated for mass rewriting.  If you're adding
     content or fixing things, please understand that your changes,
     while certainly influencing the resultant chapter, might
     themselves get lost in the mix. -->
<chapter id="svn-ch-1">

  <title>Introduction</title>


  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ======================== SECTION 1 ============================== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn-ch-1-sect-1">

    <title>Revision Control (and what svn can do for you)</title>

    <para>### TODO write me</para>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ======================== SECTION 2 ============================== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn-ch-1-sect-2">

    <title>Target audience</title>

    <para>The intended audience of this book is anyone who has used a
      version control system before, although perhaps not Subversion
      or CVS.  It assumes that the reader is computer-literate, and
      reasonably comfortable at a Unix command-line.</para>

    <para>People familiar with CVS may want to skip some of the introductory
      sections that describe Subversion's concurrent versioning model.
      Also, there is a quick guide for CVS users attached as an appendix
      <xref linkend="svn-ap-a"/></para>
    
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ======================== SECTION 3 ============================== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn-ch-1-sect-3">

    <title>History</title>

    <sect2 id="svn-ch-1-sect-3.1">

      <title>History of Revision Control</title>
      
      <para>Subversion is a free/open-source <firstterm>version
          control system</firstterm>.  That is, Subversion manages
        files over time.  The files are placed into a central
        <firstterm>repository</firstterm>.  The repository is much
        like an ordinary file server, except that it remembers every
        change ever made to your files.  This allows you to recover
        older versions of your files, or browse the history of how
        your files changed.  Many people think of a version control
        system as a sort of ``time machine.''</para>
      
      <para>Some version control systems are also <firstterm>software
          configuration management</firstterm> (SCM) systems.  These
        systems are specifically tailored to manage trees of source
        code, and have many features that are specific to software
        development (such as natively understanding programming
        languages).  Subversion, however, is not one of these
        systems; it is a general system that can be used to manage
        <emphasis>any</emphasis> sort of collection of files,
        including source code.</para>
      
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2 id="svn-ch-1-sect-3.2">
      
      <title>History of Subversion</title>
      
      <para>Subversion aims to be the successor to the
        <firstterm>Concurrent Versions System</firstterm> (CVS). You
        can find more information about CVS at <systemitem
          class="url">http://www.cvshome.org/</systemitem>.</para>
      
      <para>At the time of writing, CVS is the standard Free version
        control system used by the open-source community.  It has a
        hard-earned, well-deserved reputation as stable and useful
        software, and has a design that makes it perfect for
        open-source development.  However, it also has a number of
        problems that are difficult to fix.</para>
      
      <para>Subversion's original designers settled on a few simple
        goals.  First, it was decided that Subversion should be a
        functional replacement for CVS.  That is, it should do
        everything that CVS does, preserving the same development
        model while fixing the most obvious flaws.  Secondly, with
        existing CVS users as the first target audience, Subversion
        should be written such that any CVS user should be able to
        start using it with little effort.</para>
      
      <para>Collabnet <systemitem
          class="url">http://www.collab.net/</systemitem> provided the
        initial funding in 2000 to begin development work, and the
        effort has now blossomed into a large, open-source project
        backed by a community of free software developers.</para>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ======================== SECTION 4 ============================== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn-ch-1-sect-4">

    <title>Feature list (why svn is so nice)</title>

    <para>What sort of things does Subversion do better than CVS?  Here's a short
      list to whet your appetite:</para>

    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Advanced network layer</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The Subversion network server is Apache, and client
            and server speak WebDAV protocol to one another.  ###TODO
            Xref to Designe
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Faster network access</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A binary diffing algorithm is used to store
            and transmit deltas in both directions, regardless of whether a file
            is of text or binary type.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Meta-data</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Each file or directory has an invisible hash table
            attached.  You can invent and store any arbitrary key/value pairs you
            wish: owner, perms, icons, app-creator, mime-type, personal notes,
            etc.  This is a general-purpose feature for users.  Properties are
            versioned over time, just like file contents.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Hackability</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Subversion has no historical baggage; it is primarily
            a collection of shared C libraries with well-defined APIs.  This makes
            Subversion extremely maintainable and usable by other applications and
            languages.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Directory versioning</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The Subversion repository doesn't use RCS files like
            CVS; instead, it implements a <quote>virtual</quote>
            versioned filesystem that tracks changes to directory/file
            heirarchies over time.  Files <emphasis>and</emphasis>
            directories are versioned.  At last, there are real
            client-side <command>move</command> and
            <command>copy</command> commands.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Atomic commits</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A commit either goes into the repository
            completely, or not all.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ======================== SECTION 5 ============================== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn-ch-1-sect-5">

    <title>How to get svn binaries</title>

    <para>### TODO Write this.</para>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ======================== SECTION 6 ============================== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn-ch-1-sect-6">

    <title>How to get this book and send patches for it.</title>

    <para>### TODO Write this.</para>

  </sect1>

</chapter>

<!--
local variables: 
eval: (load-file "../tools/svnbook.el")
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->
