<chapter id="svn-ch-2">
  <title>Basic Concepts</title>

  <!-- Look, I know there are a lot of firstterm tags here.  But
  remember the name of the chapter: Basic Concepts.  That pretty much
  means this chapter is all about defining terms for the first time,
  right?  :-)-->

    
  <simplesect>
    <para>This chapter is a short, casual introduction to Subversion.
      If you're new to version control, this chapter is definitely for
      you.  We begin with a discussion of general version control
      concepts, work our way into the specific ideas behind
      Subversion, and show some simple examples of Subversion in
      use.</para>
    
    <para>Even though the examples in this chapter show people sharing
      collections of program source code, keep in mind that Subversion
      can manage any sort of file collection -- it's not limited to
      helping computer programmers.</para>
  </simplesect>
  
  
  <sect1 id="svn-ch2-sect-1" > 
    <title>The Repository</title>  
    
    <para>Subversion is a centralized system for sharing information.
      At its core is a <firstterm>repository</firstterm>, which is a
      central store of data.  The repository stores information in the
      form of a <firstterm>filesystem tree</firstterm> -- a typical
      hierarchy of files and directories.  Any number of
      <firstterm>clients</firstterm> connect to the repository, and
      then read or write to these files.  By writing data, a client
      makes the information available to others; by reading data, the
      client receives information from others.</para>

    <figure id="svn-ch2-dia1">
      <title>A typical client/server system</title>
      <graphic fileref="images/ch02dia1.png"/>
    </figure>
    
    <para>So why is this interesting?  So far, this sounds like the
      definition of a typical file server.  And indeed, the repository
      <emphasis>is</emphasis> a kind of file server, but it's not your
      usual breed.  What makes the Subversion repository special is
      that <emphasis>it remembers every change</emphasis> ever written
      to it: every change to every file, and even changes to the
      directory tree itself, such as the addition, deletion, and
      rearrangement of files and directories.</para>

    <para>When a client reads data from the repository, it normally
      sees only the latest version of the filesystem tree.  But the
      client also has the ability to view
      <emphasis>previous</emphasis> states of the filesystem.  For
      example, a client can ask historical questions like, "what did
      this directory contain last Wednesday?", or "who was the last
      person to change this file, and what changes did they make?"
      These are the sorts of questions that are at the heart of any
      <firstterm>version control system</firstterm>: systems that are
      designed to record and track changes to data over time.
    </para>

  </sect1>


  <!-- the philosophical section --> 
  <sect1 id="svn-ch-2-sect-2">
    <title>Versioning Models</title>
    
    <sect2 id="svn-ch-2-sect-2.1">
      <title>The Problem of File-Sharing</title>
      
      <para>All version control systems have to solve the same
        fundamental problem: how will the system allow users to share
        information, but prevent them from accidentally stepping on
        each other's feet?  It's all too easy for users to
        accidentally overwrite each other's changes in the
        repository.</para>

      <para>Consider this hypothetical example.  Suppose we have two
        co-workers, Jane and Joe.  They each decide to edit the same
        repository file at the same time.  If Joe saves his changes to
        the repository first, then it's possible that (a few moments
        later) Jane could accidentally overwrite them with her own new
        version of the file.  While Joe's version of the file won't be
        lost forever (because the system remembers every change), any
        changes Joe made <emphasis>won't</emphasis> be present in
        Jane's newer version of the file, because she never saw Joe's
        changes to begin with.  Joe's work is still effectively
        lost&mdash;or at least missing from the latest version of the
        file&mdash;and probably by accident.  This is definitely a
        situation we want to avoid!</para>

      <figure id="svn-ch2-dia2">
        <title>The problem to avoid</title>
        <graphic fileref="images/ch02dia2.png"/>
      </figure>

      </sect2>
    
    <sect2 id="svn-ch-2-sect-2.2">
      <title>The Lock-Modify-Unlock Solution</title>
      
      <para>Many version control systems use a
        <firstterm>lock-modify-unlock</firstterm> model to address
        this problem, which is a very simple, traditional solution.
        In such a system, the repository allows only one person to
        change a file at a time.  Such a system requires Joe to first
        "lock" the file before he can begin making changes to it.
        Locking a file is a lot like borrowing a book from the
        library; if Joe has locked a file, then Jane cannot make any
        changes to it.  If she tries to lock the file, the repository
        will deny the request.  All she can do is read the file, and
        wait for Joe to finish his changes and release his lock.
        After Joe unlocks the file, his turn is over, and now Jane can
        take her turn by locking and editing.</para>
      
      <figure id="svn-ch2-dia3">
        <title>The lock-modify-unlock solution</title>
        <graphic fileref="images/ch02dia3.png"/>
      </figure>
      
      <para>The problem with the lock-modify-unlock model is that it's
        a bit restrictive, and often becomes a roadblock for
        users:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Sometimes Joe will lock a file and then forget
            about it.  Meanwhile, because Jane is still waiting to
            edit the file, her hands are tied.  And then Joe goes on
            vacation.  Now Jane has to get an administrator to release
            Joe's lock.  The situation ends up causing a lot of
            unnecessary delay and wasted time.</para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>What if Joe is editing the beginning of a text
            file, and Jane simply wants to edit the end of the same
            file?  These changes don't overlap at all.  They could
            easily edit the file simultaneously, and no great harm
            would come, assuming the changes were properly merged
            together.  There's no need for them to take turns in this
            situation.</para></listitem>
    
        <listitem><para>Pretend that Joe locks and edits file A, while
            Jane simultaneously locks and edits file B.  But suppose
            that A and B depend on one another, and the changes made
            to each are semantically incompatible.  Suddenly A and B
            don't work together anymore, and the locking system was
            powerless to prevent it&mdash;yet the locking system somehow
            provided a sense of false security, when it shouldn't
            have.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      </sect2>

    <sect2 id="svn-ch-2-sect-2.3">
      <title>The Copy-Modify-Merge Solution</title>
      
      <para>Subversion, CVS, and other version control systems use a
        <firstterm>copy-modify-merge</firstterm> model as an
        alternative to locking.  In this model, each user's client
        reads the repository and creates a personal <firstterm>working
        copy</firstterm> of the file or project.  Users then work in
        parallel, modifying their private copies.  Finally, the
        private copies are merged together into a new, final version.
        The version control system often assists with the merging, but
        ultimately a human being is responsible for making it happen
        correctly.</para>
      
      <para>Here's an example.  Say that Joe and Jane each create
        working copies of the same project, copied from the
        repository.  They work concurrently, and make changes to the
        same file "A" within their copies.  Jane saves her changes to
        the repository first.  When Joe attempts to save his changes
        later, the repository informs him that his file A is
        <firstterm>out-of-date</firstterm>.  In other words, that file
        A in the repository has somehow changed since he last copied
        it.  So Joe asks his client to <firstterm>merge</firstterm>
        any new changes from the repository into his working copy of
        file A.  Chances are that Jane's changes don't overlap with
        his own; so once he has both sets of changes integrated, he
        saves his working copy back to the repository.</para>

      <figure id="svn-ch2-dia4">
        <title>The copy-modify-merge solution</title>
        <graphic fileref="images/ch02dia4.png"/>
      </figure>
      
      <figure id="svn-ch2-dia5">
        <title>...copy-modify-merge continued</title>
        <graphic fileref="images/ch02dia5.png"/>
      </figure>

      <para>But what if Jane's changes <emphasis>do</emphasis> overlap
        with Joe's changes?  What then?  This situation is called a
        <firstterm>conflict</firstterm>, and it's usually not much of
        a problem.  When Joe asks his client to merge the the latest
        repository changes into his working copy, his copy of file A
        is somehow flagged as being in a state of conflict: he'll be
        able to see both sets of conflicting changes, and manually
        choose between them.  Note that software can't automatically
        resolve conflicts; only humans are capable of understanding
        and making intelligent choices.  Once Joe has manually
        resolved the overlapping changes (perhaps by discussing the
        conflict with Jane!), he can safely save the hand-merged file
        back to the repository.</para>

      <para>The copy-modify-merge model may sound a bit chaotic, but
        in practice, it runs extremely smoothly.  Users can work in
        parallel, never waiting for one another.  When they work on
        the same files, it turns out that most of their concurrent
        changes don't overlap at all; conflicts are infrequent.  And
        the amount of time it takes to resolve conflicts is far less
        than the time lost by a locking system.</para>

      <para>In the end, it all comes down to one critical factor: user
        communication.  When users communicate poorly, both syntactic
        and semantic conflicts increase.  No system can force users to
        communicate perfectly, and no system can detect semantic
        conflicts.  So there's no point in being lulled into a false
        promise that a locking system will somehow prevent conflicts;
        in practice, locking seems to inhibit productivity more than
        anything else.</para>
      
    </sect2>
    
  </sect1>
  
  <!-- How svn implements the philosophy -->
  <sect1 id="svn-ch-2-sect-3">
    <title>Subversion in action</title>
    
    <sect2 id="svn-ch-2-sect-3.1">
      <title>Working copies</title>
      
      <para>You've already read about working copies; now we'll
        demonstrate how the Subversion client creates and uses
        them.</para>
      
      <para>A Subversion working copy is an ordinary directory tree on
        your local system, containing a collection of files.  You can
        edit these files however you wish, and if they're source code
        files, you can compile your program from them in the usual
        way.  Your working copy is your own private work area:
        Subversion will never incorporate other people's changes, nor
        make your own changes available to others, until you
        explicitly tell it to do so.</para>

      <para>After you've made some changes to the files in your
        working copy and verified that they work properly, Subversion
        provides commands to "publish" your changes to the other
        people working with you on your project (by writing to the
        repository).  If other people publish their own changes,
        Subversion provides commands to merge those changes into your
        working directory (by reading from the repository).</para>

      <para>A working copy also contains some extra files, created and
        maintained by Subversion, to help it carry out these commands.
        In particular, each directory in your working copy contains a
        subdirectory named <filename>.svn</filename>, also known as
        the working copy <firstterm>administrative
        directory</firstterm>.  The files in each administrative
        directory help Subversion recognize which files contain
        unpublished changes, and which files are out-of-date with
        respect to others' work.</para>
      
      <para>A typical Subversion repository often holds the files (or
        source code) for several projects; usually, each project is a
        subdirectory in the repository's filesystem tree.  In this
        arrangement, a user's working copy will usually correspond to
        a particular subtree of the repository.</para>

      <para>For example, suppose you have a repository that contains
        two software projects.</para>

      <figure id="svn-ch2-dia6">
        <title>The repository's filesystem</title>
        <graphic fileref="images/ch02dia6.png"/>
      </figure>
      
      <para>In other words, the repository's root directory has two
        subdirectories: <filename>paint</filename> and
        <filename>write</filename>.</para>

      <para>To get a working copy, you must <firstterm>check
          out</firstterm> some subtree of the repository.  If you
          check out <filename>/write</filename>, you will get a
          working copy like this: </para>

<screen>
$ svn checkout http://svn.example.com/repos/write
A  write
A  write/Makefile
A  write/document.c
A  write/search.c

$ ls -a write
Makefile  document.c  search.c  .svn/
</screen>

      <para>Your working copy is a personal copy of the repository's
        <filename>/write</filename> directory, with one additional
        entry&mdash;<filename>.svn</filename>&mdash;which holds the
        extra information needed by Subversion, as mentioned
        earlier.</para>
      
      <para>Suppose you make changes to
        <filename>search.c</filename>.  Since the
        <filename>.svn</filename> directory remembers the file's
        modification date and original contents, Subversion can tell
        that you've changed the file.  However, Subversion does not
        make your changes public until you explicitly tell it to.  The
        act of publishing your changes is more commonly known as
        <firstterm>committing</firstterm> changes to the
        repository.</para>

      <para>To publish your changes to others, you can use
        Subversion's <command>commit</command> command:</para>

<screen>
$ svn commit search.c
Sending search.c
Transmitting file data..
Committed revision 57.
</screen>

      <para>Now your changes to <filename>search.c</filename> have
        been committed to the repository; if another user checks out a
        working copy of <filename>/write</filename>, they will see
        your changes in the latest version of the file.</para>

      <para>Suppose you have a collaborator, Felix, who checked out a
        working copy of <filename>/write</filename> at the same time
        you did.  When you commit your change to
        <filename>search.c</filename>, Felix's working copy is left
        unchanged; Subversion only modifies working directories at the
        user's request.</para>

      <para>To bring his work up to date, Felix can ask Subversion to
        <firstterm>update</firstterm> his working copy, by using the
        Subversion <command>update</command> command.  This will
        incorporate your changes into his working copy, as well as any
        others that have been committed since he checked it
        out.</para>

<screen>
$ pwd
/home/felix/write

$ ls -a 
.svn/ Makefile document.c search.c

$ svn update
U search.c
</screen>

      <para>The output from the <command>svn update</command> command
        indicates that Subversion updated the contents of
        <filename>search.c</filename>.  Note that Felix didn't need to
        specify which files to update; Subversion uses the information
        in the <filename>.svn</filename> directory, and further
        information in the repository, to decide which files need to
        be brought up to date.</para>
      
    </sect2>
    
    
    <sect2 id="svn-ch-2-sect-3.2">
      <title>Revisions</title>

      <para>A <command>svn commit</command> operation can publish
        changes to any number of files and directories as a single
        atomic transaction.  In your working copy, you can change
        files' contents, create, delete, rename and copy files and
        directories, and then commit the complete set of changes as a
        unit.</para>

      <para>In the repository, each commit is treated as an atomic
        transaction: either all the commit's changes take place, or
        none of them take place.  Subversion tries to retain this
        atomicity in the face of program crashes, system crashes,
        network problems, and other users' actions.</para>

      <para>Each time the repository accepts a commit, this creates a
        new state of the filesystem tree, called a
        <firstterm>revision</firstterm>.  Each revision is assigned a
        unique natural number, one greater than the number of the
        previous revision.  The initial revision of a freshly created
        repository is numbered zero, and consists of nothing but an
        empty root directory.</para>
      
      <para>A nice way to visualize the repository is as a series of
        trees.  Imagine an array of revision numbers, starting at 0,
        stretching from left to right.  Each revision number has a
        filesystem tree hanging below it, and each tree is a
        "snapshot" of the way the repository looked after each
        commit. </para>
      
      <figure id="svn-ch2-dia7">
        <title>The repository</title>
        <graphic fileref="images/ch02dia7.png"/>
      </figure>


        <sidebar>
        <title>Global revision numbers</title>
         
        <para>Unlike those of many other version control systems,
          Subversion's revision numbers apply to <emphasis>entire
          trees</emphasis>, not individual files.  Each revision
          number selects an entire tree, a particular state of the
          repository after some committed change.  Another way to
          think about it is that revision N represents the state of
          the repository filesystem after the Nth commit.  When a
          Subversion user talks about ``revision 5 of
          <filename>foo.c</filename>'', they really mean
          ``<filename>foo.c</filename> as it appears in revision 5.''
          Notice that in general, revisions N and M of a file do
          <emphasis>not</emphasis> necessarily differ!  Because CVS
          uses per-file revisions numbers, CVS users might want to
          look at Appendix A, "SVN for CVS Users", for more details.
          <!-- ### add xref here! --></para>
        </sidebar>

      <para>It's important to note that working copies do not always
        correspond to any single revision in the repository; they may
        contain files from several different revisions.  For example,
        suppose you check out a working copy from a repository whose
        most recent revision is 4:</para>

<screen>
write/Makefile:4
      document.c:4
      search.c:4
</screen>

      <para>At the moment, this working directory corresponds exactly
        to revision 4 in the repository.  However, suppose you make a
        change to <filename>search.c</filename>, and commit that
        change.  Assuming no other commits have taken place, your
        commit will create revision 5 of the repository, and your
        working copy will now look like this:</para>

<screen>
write/Makefile:4
      document.c:4
      search.c:5
</screen>

      <para>Suppose that, at this point, Felix commits a change to
        <filename>document.c</filename>, creating revision 6.  If you
        use <command>svn update</command> to bring your working copy
        up to date, then it will look like this:</para>

<screen>
write/Makefile:6
      document.c:6
      search.c:6
</screen>

      <para>Felix's changes to <filename>document.c</filename> will
        appear in your working copy, and your change will still be
        present in <filename>search.c</filename>.  In this example,
        the text of <filename>Makefile</filename> is identical in
        revisions 4, 5, and 6, but Subversion will mark your working
        copy of <filename>Makefile</filename> with revision 6 to
        indicate that it is still current.  So, after you do a clean
        update at the top of your working copy, it will generally
        correspond to exactly one revision in the repository.</para>

    </sect2>
    
    
    <sect2 id="svn-ch-2-sect-3.3">
      <title>How working copies track the repository</title>
      
      <para>For each file in a working directory, Subversion records
        two essential pieces of information in the
        <filename>.svn/</filename> administrative area:</para>
      
      
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>what revision your working file is based on
            (this is called the file's <firstterm>working
             revision</firstterm>), and</para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>a timestamp recording when the local copy was
            last updated by the repository.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Given this information, by talking to the repository,
        Subversion can tell which of the following four states a
        working file is in:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Unchanged, and current</term> 

          <listitem><para>The file is unchanged in the working
          directory, and no changes to that file have been committed
          to the repository since its working revision.  A
          <command>svn commit</command> of the file will do nothing,
          and a <command>svn update</command> of the file will do
          nothing. </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Locally changed, and current</term>

          <listitem><para>The file has been changed in the working
          directory, and no changes to that file have been committed
          to the repository since its base revision.  There are local
          changes that have not been committed to the repository, thus
          a <command>svn commit</command> of the file will succeed in
          publishing your changes, and a <command>svn update</command>
          of the file will do nothing.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Unchanged, and out-of-date</term> 

          <listitem><para>The file has not been changed in the working
          directory, but it has been changed in the repository.  The
          file should eventually be updated, to make it current with
          the public revision.  A <command>svn commit</command> of the
          file will do nothing, and a <command>svn update</command> of
          the file fold the latest changes into your working
          copy.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Locally changed, and out-of-date</term>

          <listitem><para>The file has been changed both in the
          working directory, and in the repository.  A <command>svn
          commit</command> of the file will fail with an "out-of-date"
          error.  The file should be updated first; a <command>svn
          update</command> command will attempt to merge the public
          changes with the local changes.  If Subversion can't
          complete the merge in a plausible way automatically, it
          leaves it to the user to resolve the
          conflict.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      
      
      <para>This may sound like a lot to keep track of, but as you
        will learn in a later chapter, the <command>svn
        status</command> command will show you the state of any item
        in your working copy.  <!-- ###TODO xref the relevant section that
        details 'status' -->
      </para>
     
    </sect2>
    
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="svn-ch-2-sect-">
    <title>Summary</title>
    
    <para>We've covered a number of fundamental Subversion concepts in
    this chapter:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>We've introduced the notions of the central repository,
          the client working copy, and the array of repository
          revision trees.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>We've seen some simple examples of how two collaborators
        can use Subversion to publish and receive changes from one
        another, using the 'copy-modify-merge' model.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>We've talked a bit about the way Subversion tracks and
          manages information in a working copy.</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>At this point, you should have a good idea of how Subversion
    works in the most general sense.  Armed with this knowledge, you
    should now be ready to jump into the next chapter, which is a more
    detailed, guided tour of Subversion's commands and
    features. </para>
      
  </sect1>

</chapter>

<!--
local variables: 
eval: (load-file "../tools/svnbook.el")
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->
