<chapter id="svn-ch-3">
  <title>Guided Tour</title>

  <simplesect>

    <para>Now we will go into the details of using Subversion in your
      day to day work.  By the time you reach the end of this chapter,
      you will be able to perform almost all the tasks you need to use
      Subversion in a normal day's work.  You'll start with an initial
      checkout of your code, and walk through making changes and
      examining those changes. You'll also see how to bring changes
      made by others into your working copy, examine them, and work
      through any conflicts that might arise.</para>

    <para>Note that this chapter is not meant to be an exhaustive list
      of all Subversion's commands&mdash;rather, it's a conversational
      introduction to the most common Subversion tasks you'll
      encounter.  For a complete reference of all commands, see <xref
      linkend="svn-ch-8"/>.</para>

  </simplesect>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ======================== SECTION 1 ============================== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn-ch-3-sect-1">
    <title>Help!</title>


    <para>Before reading on, here is the most important command you'll
      ever need when using Subversion: <command>svn help</command>.
      The Subversion command-line client tries to be
      self-documenting&mdash;at any time, a quick <command>svn help
      &lt;subcommand&gt;</command> will describe the syntax, switches,
      and behavior of the <command>subcommand</command>.</para>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ======================== SECTION 2 ============================== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn-ch-3-sect-2">
    <title>Import</title>

    <para><command>svn import</command> is used to import a new
    project into a Subversion repository.  While this is most likely
    the very first thing you will do when you set up your Subversion
    server, it's not something that happens very often.  For a
    detailed description of import, see <xref linkend="svn-ch-5"/>.
    </para>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ======================== SECTION 3 ============================== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn-ch-3-sect-3">
    <title>Initial Checkout</title>

    <para>Most of the time, you will start using a Subversion
      repository by doing a <firstterm>checkout</firstterm> of your
      project.  <quote>Checking out</quote> will provide you with a
      local copy of the <literal>HEAD</literal> (latest revision) of
      the Subversion repository that you specify on the command
      line.</para>
    

    <screen>
$ svn co http://svn.collab.net/repos/svn/trunk
A  trunk/subversion.dsw
A  trunk/svn_check.dsp
A  trunk/COMMITTERS
A  trunk/configure.in
A  trunk/IDEAS
&hellip;
Checked out revision 2499.
    </screen>
    
    <sidebar>
      <title>Repository Layout</title>

      <para>If you're wondering what <literal>trunk</literal> is all
        about in the above URL, it's part of the way that we recommend
        you lay out your Subversion repository. That is, when you
        create a new Subversion repository, you should make three
        top-level directories: <literal>trunk</literal>,
        <literal>tags</literal>, and <literal>branches</literal>.
        This may seem a little odd at the moment, but we'll talk a lot
        more about these in <xref linkend="svn-ch-5"/>.</para>

    </sidebar>

    <para>Although the above example checks out the trunk directory,
      you can just as easily checkout any deep subdirectory of a
      repository by specifying the subdirectory in the checkout
      URL:</para>
    
    <screen>
$ svn co http://svn.collab.net/repos/svn/trunk/doc/book/tools
A  tools/readme-dblite.html
A  tools/fo-stylesheet.xsl
A  tools/svnbook.el
A  tools/dtd
A  tools/dtd/dblite.dtd
&hellip;
Checked out revision 3678.
    </screen>
    
    <para>Since Subversion uses a <quote>copy-modify-merge</quote>
      model instead of <quote>lock-modify-unlock,</quote> (See <xref
      linkend="svn-ch-2"/>) you're now ready to start making changes
      to the files that you've checked out, known collectively as your
      <firstterm>working copy</firstterm>. You can even delete the
      entire working copy and forget about it&mdash;there's
      no need to notify the Subversion server unless you're ready to
      <firstterm>check in</firstterm> changes, a new file, or even a
      directory.</para>

    <sidebar>
      <title>What's with the <filename>.svn</filename> directory?</title>

      <para>Every directory in a working copy contains an
        <firstterm>administrative area</firstterm>, a subdirectory
        named <filename>.svn</filename>.  Usually, directory listing
        commands won't show this subdirectory, but it is nevertheless
        an important directory.  Whatever you do, don't delete or
        change anything in the administrative area!  Subversion
        depends on it to manage your working copy.</para>

    </sidebar>

    <para>While you can certainly check out a working copy with the
      url of the repository as the only argument, you can also specify
      a directory after your repository url.  This places your working
      copy into the new directory that you name.  For example:</para>
    
    <screen>
$ svn co http://svn.collab.net/repos/svn/trunk subv
A  subv/subversion.dsw
A  subv/svn_check.dsp
A  subv/COMMITTERS
A  subv/configure.in
A  subv/IDEAS
&hellip;
Checked out revision 2499.
    </screen>
    
    <para>That will place your working copy in a directory named
      <literal>subv</literal> instead of a directory named
      <literal>trunk</literal> as was the case above.</para>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ======================== SECTION 4 ============================== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn-ch-3-sect-4">
    <title>Basic Workcycle</title>

    <para>Subversion has numerous features, options, bells and whistles, but on
      a day-to-day basis, odds are that you will only use a few of them. In
      this section we'll run through the most common things that you might
      find yourself doing with Subversion in the course of a day's work.</para>
    
    <para>The typical work cycle looks like this</para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>Update your working copy</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Make changes</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Examine your changes</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Merge others' changes</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Commit your changes</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

    <sect2 id="svn-ch-3-sect-4.1">
      <title>Update Your Working Copy</title>

      <para>When working on a project with a team, you'll want to
        <firstterm>update</firstterm> your working copy: that is,
        receive any changes from other developers on the project.
        <command>svn update</command> brings your working copy
        in sync with the latest revision in the repository.</para>
      
      <screen>
$ svn up
U  ./foo.c
U  ./bar.c
Updated to revision 2.
      </screen>
      
      <para>In this case, someone else checked in modifications to
        both <filename>foo.c</filename> and <filename>bar.c</filename>
        since the last time you updated, and Subversion has updated
        your working copy to include those changes.</para>
      
      <para>Let's examine the output of <command>svn update</command>
        a bit more.  When the server sends changes to your working
        copy, a letter code is displayed next to each item to let you
        know what actions Subversion performed to bring your working
        copy up to date:</para>

      <variablelist>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><computeroutput>U      foo</computeroutput></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>File <filename>foo</filename> was
              <computeroutput>U</computeroutput>pdated (received changes
              from the server).</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><computeroutput>A      foo</computeroutput></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>File or directory <filename>foo</filename> was
              <computeroutput>A</computeroutput>dded to your working
              copy.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><computeroutput>D      foo</computeroutput></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>File or directory <filename>foo</filename> was
              <computeroutput>D</computeroutput>eleted from your working
              copy.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        
        <varlistentry>
          <term><computeroutput>R      foo</computeroutput></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>File or directory <filename>foo</filename> was
              <computeroutput>R</computeroutput>eplaced in your working
              copy; that is, <filename>foo</filename> was deleted, and a
              new item with the same name was added.  While they may have
              the same name, the repository considers them to be distinct
              objects with distinct histories.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><computeroutput>G      foo</computeroutput></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>File <filename>foo</filename> received new changes
              from the repository, but your local copy of the file had
              changes that you made.  The changes did not intersect,
              however, so Subversion has
              mer<computeroutput>G</computeroutput>ed the repository's
              changes into the file without a problem.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><computeroutput>C      foo</computeroutput></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>File <filename>foo</filename> received
              <computeroutput>C</computeroutput>onflicting changes from
              the server.  The changes from the server directly overlap
              your own changes to the file.  No need to panic, though.
              This overlap needs to be resolved by a human (you); we
              discuss this situation later in this chapter.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

      </variablelist>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="svn-ch-3-sect-4.2">
      <title>Make Changes to Your Working Copy</title>
      
      <para>Now you can to get to work and make changes in your
        working copy. It's usually most convenient to create a
        <quote>task</quote> for yourself, such as writing a new
        feature, fixing a bug, etc.  The Subversion commands that you
        will use here are <command>svn add</command>, <command>svn
        delete</command>, <command>svn copy</command>, and
        <command>svn move</command>.  However, if you are merely
        editing a file (or files) that is already in Subversion, you
        may not need to use any of these commands until you commit.</para>
      
      <variablelist>
        <title>Changes you can make to your working copy:</title>
        
        <varlistentry>
          <term>File changes</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>This is the simplest sort of change.  Unlike other
              version control systems, you don't need to tell
              Subversion that you intend to change a file; just make
              your changes.  Subversion will be able to automatically
              detect which files have been changed.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Tree changes</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>You can ask Subversion to <quote>mark</quote> files
              and directories for scheduled removal, addition,
              copying, or moving.  While these changes may take place
              immediately in your working copy, no additions or
              removals will happen in the repository until you decide
              to commit.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

      </variablelist>
      
      <para>To make file changes, just use your text editor, word
        processor, or graphics program&mdash;whatever tool you would
        normally use.  A file needn't be in text-format; Subversion
        handles binary files just as easily as it handles text file
        (and just as efficiently too).</para>
      
      <para>Here is an overview of the four Subversion subcommands
        that you'll use most often to make tree changes (we'll cover
        <command>svn import</command> and <command>svn mkdir</command>
        later).</para>
      
      <variablelist>
        
        <varlistentry>
          <term><command>svn add foo</command></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Schedule <filename>foo</filename> to be added to the
              repository.  When you next commit,
              <filename>foo</filename> will become a permanent child
              of its parent directory.  Note that if
              <filename>foo</filename> is a directory, only the
              directory itself will be scheduled for addition.  If you
              want to add its contents as well, pass the
              <option>--recursive</option> (<option>-r</option>) switch.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><command>svn delete foo</command></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Schedule <filename>foo</filename> to be deleted from
              the repository.  If <filename>foo</filename> is a file,
              it is immediately deleted from your working
              copy&mdash;but it can be recovered with <command>svn
              revert</command> (discussed later).  If
              <filename>foo</filename> is a directory, it is not
              deleted, but Subversion schedules it for deletion.  When
              you commit your changes, <filename>foo</filename> will
              be removed from your working copy and the repository.
              <footnote><para>Of course, nothing is ever totally
              deleted from the repository&mdash;just from the HEAD of
              the repository.  You can get back anything you delete by
              checking out (or updating your working copy) to a
              revision earlier than the one in which you deleted
              it.</para> </footnote></para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><command>svn copy foo bar</command></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Create new item <filename>bar</filename> as a
              duplicate of <filename>foo</filename>.
              <filename>bar</filename> is automatically scheduled for
              addition.  When <filename>bar</filename> is added to the
              repository on the next commit, its copy-history is
              recorded (as having originally come from
              <filename>foo</filename>.)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><command>svn move foo bar</command></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>This command is exactly the same as running
              <command>svn cp foo bar; svn rm foo</command>.  That is,
              <filename>bar</filename> is scheduled for addition as a
              copy of <filename>foo</filename>, and
              <filename>foo</filename> is scheduled for removal.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

      </variablelist>

      <sidebar>
        <title>Changing the repository without committing</title>
        
        <para>Earlier in this chapter, we said that you have to commit
          any changes that you make in order for the repository to
          reflect these changes. That's not entirely true&mdash;there
          <emphasis>are</emphasis> some use-cases that immediately
          commit tree changes to the repository.  This only happens
          when a subcommand is operating directly on a URL, rather
          than on a working-copy path. (In particular, specific uses
          of <command>svn mkdir</command>, <command>svn cp</command>,
          <command>svn mv</command>, and <command>svn rm</command> can
          work with URLs).</para>

        <para>URL operations behave in this manner because commands
          that operate on a working copy can use the working copy as a
          sort of <quote>staging area</quote> to set up your changes
          before committing them to the repository.  Commands that
          operate on URLs don't have this luxury, so when you operate
          directly on a URL, any of the above actions represent an
          immediate commit.</para>

      </sidebar>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="svn-ch-3-sect-4.3">
      <title>Examine Your Changes</title>
      
      <sect3 id="svn-ch-3-sect-4.3.1">
        <title><command>svn status</command></title>

        <para>Once you've finished making changes, you need to commit
          them to the repository, but before you do so, it's usually a
          good idea to take a look at exactly what you've changed.  By
          examining your changes before you commit, you can not only
          make a more accurate log message, but you may discover that
          you've inadvertently changed a file, and this gives you a
          chance to revert those changes before committing.  You can
          see exactly what changes you've made by using <command>svn
          status</command>, <command>svn diff</command>, and
          <command>svn revert</command> to find out what files have
          changed where and possibly remove these changes.</para>
      
        <para>Subversion has been optimized to help you with this
          task, and is able to do many things without communicating
          with the repository.  In particular, your working copy
          contains a secret cached <quote>pristine</quote> copy of
          each version controlled file within the
          <filename>.svn</filename> area.  Because of this, Subversion
          can quickly show you how your working files have changed, or
          even allow you to undo your changes without contacting the
          repository.</para>

        <para>You'll probably use the <command>svn status</command>
          command more than any other Subversion command.</para>
        
        <sidebar>
          <title>CVS Users note</title>
          
          <para>You're probably used to using <command>cvs
              update</command> to see what changes you've made to your
            working copy.  <command>svn status</command> will give
            you all the information you need regarding what has
            changed in your working copy&mdash;without accessing the
            repository.</para>
        
          <para>In Subversion, <command>update</command> does just
            that&mdash;it updates your working copy with any changes
            committed to the repository since the last time you've
            updated your working copy.  You'll have to break the habit
            of using the <command>update</command> command to see what
            local modifications you've made.</para>

        </sidebar>
        
        <para> If you run <command>svn status</command> at the top of
          your working copy with no arguments, it will detect all file
          and tree changes you've made.  This example is designed to
          show all the different status codes that <command>svn
          status</command> can return.  Note that the text in
          <literal>[]</literal> is not printed by <command>svn
          status</command>.</para>
      
        <screen>
$ svn status
  L    ./abc.c               [svn has a lock in its .svn directory for abc.c]
M      ./bar.c               [the content in bar.c has local modifications]
 M     ./baz.c               [baz.c has property but no content modifications]
?      ./foo.o               [svn doesn't manage foo.o]
!      ./foo.c               [svn knows foo.c but a non-svn program deleted it]
~      ./qux                 [versioned as dir, but is file, or vice versa]
A  +   ./moved_dir           [added with history of where it came from]
M  +   ./moved_dir/README    [added with history and has local modifications]
D      ./stuff/fish.c        [this file is scheduled for deletion]
A      ./stuff/things/bloo.h [this file is scheduled for addition]
        </screen><!-- ###TODO Should the above be a table? -Fitz -->
      
        <para>In this output format <command>svn status</command>
          prints four columns of characters followed by several
          whitespace characters followed by a file or directory name.
          The first column tells the status of a file or directory
          and/or its contents.  The codes printed here are:</para>


        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><computeroutput>       file_or_dir</computeroutput></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The file or directory has not been added or deleted,
                nor have <filename>file_or_dir</filename>'s contents
                been modified if it is a file.  This line is printed
                only if you use <command>svn status -v</command></para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><computeroutput>A      file_or_dir</computeroutput></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The file or directory
                <filename>file_or_dir</filename> has been scheduled for
                addition into the repository.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><computeroutput>M      file</computeroutput></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The contents of file <filename>file</filename> have
                been modified.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><computeroutput>D      file_or_dir</computeroutput></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The file or directory
                <filename>file_or_dir</filename> has been scheduled for
                deletion from the repository.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><computeroutput>?      file_or_dir</computeroutput></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The file or directory
                <filename>file_or_dir</filename> is not under version
                control.  You can silence the question marks by either
                passing the <option>--quiet</option>
                (<option>-q</option>) switch to <command>svn
                status</command>, or by setting the
                <literal>svn:ignore</literal> property on the parent
                directory.</para>

              <para>By default, <command>svn status</command> ignores
                files matching the regular expressions
                <literal>*.o</literal>, <literal>*.lo</literal>,
                <literal>*.la</literal>, <literal>#*#</literal>,
                <literal>*.rej</literal>, <literal>*~</literal>, and
                <literal>.#*</literal>.  If you want additional files
                ignored, set the <literal>svn:ignore</literal> property
                on the parent directory.  If you want to see the status
                of all the files in the repository regardless of
                <command>svn status</command> and
                <command>svn:ignore</command>'s regular expressions,
                then use the <option>--no-ignore</option> command line
                option.  See <xref linkend="svn-ch-6-sect-2.1.3"/> for
                more information.</para>

            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><computeroutput>!      file_or_dir</computeroutput></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The file or directory
                <filename>file_or_dir</filename> is under version
                control but is missing from the working copy.  This
                happens if the file or directory is removed using a
                non-Subversion command.  A quick <command>svn
                  up</command> or <command>svn revert
                  file_or_dir</command> will restore the missing file from
                its cached pristine copy (directories must be refetched
                from the repository since the pristine copies are kept
                <emphasis>inside</emphasis> of the directory.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><computeroutput>~     file_or_dir</computeroutput></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The file or directory
                <filename>file_or_dir</filename> is in the repository as
                one kind of object, but what's actually in your working
                copy is some other kind.  For example, Subversion might
                have a file in the repository, but you removed the file
                and created a directory in its place, without using the
                <command>svn delete</command> nor <command>svn add</command>
                commands.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

        </variablelist>

        <para>The second column tells the status of a file or
          directory's properties.  If an
          <computeroutput>M</computeroutput> appears in the second
          column, then the properties have been modified, otherwise a
          whitespace will be printed.</para>
        
        <para>The third column will only show whitespace or an
          <computeroutput>L</computeroutput> which means that
          Subversion has locked the item in
          the<filename>.svn</filename> working area.  You will see an
          <computeroutput>L</computeroutput> if you run <command>svn
          status</command> in a directory where an <command>svn
          commit</command> is in progress&mdash;perhaps when you are
          editing the log message.  If Subversion is not running, then
          presumably Subversion was forcibly quit or died and the lock
          needs to be cleaned up by running <command>svn
          cleanup</command> (more about that later in this chapter).
          Locks typically appear if a Subversion command is
          interrupted before completion.</para>
        
        <para>The fourth column will only show whitespace or a
          <computeroutput>+</computeroutput> which means that the file
          or directory is scheduled to be added or modified with
          additional attached history.  This typically happens when you
          <command>svn move</command> or <command>svn copy</command> a file
          or directory.  If you see
          <computeroutput>A&nbsp;&nbsp;+</computeroutput>, this means
          the item is scheduled for addition-with-history.  It could be
          a file, or the root of a copied directory.
          <quote><computeroutput>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;+</computeroutput></quote>
          means the item is part of a subtree scheduled for
          addition-with-history, i.e. some parent got copied, and it's
          just coming along for the ride.
          <computeroutput>M&nbsp;&nbsp;+</computeroutput> means the item
          is part of a subtree scheduled for addition-with-history,
          <emphasis>and</emphasis> it has local modifications.  When you
          commit, first the parent will be added-with-history (copied),
          which means this file will automatically exist in the copy.
          Then the local modifications will be uploaded into the
          copy.</para>
        
        <para>If you pass a specific path to <command>svn
            status</command>, it gives you information about that item
            alone:</para>
        
        <screen>
$ svn status stuff/fish.c
D      stuff/fish.c
        </screen>
        
        <para><command>svn status</command> also has a
          <option>--verbose</option> (<option>-v</option>) switch,
          which will show you the status of <emphasis>every</emphasis>
          item in your working copy, even if it has not been changed
          in your working copy:</para>
           
        <screen>
$ svn status --verbose
M               44        23    sally     ./README
                44        30    sally     ./INSTALL
M               44        20    harry     ./bar.c
                44        18    ira       ./stuff
                44        35    harry     ./stuff/trout.c
D               44        19    ira       ./stuff/fish.c
                44        21    sally     ./stuff/things
A                0         ?     ?        ./stuff/things/bloo.h
                44        36    harry     ./stuff/things/gloo.c
        </screen>
           
        <para>This is the <quote>long form</quote> output of
          <command>svn status</command>.  The first column remains
          same, but the second column shows the working-revision of
          the item.  The third and fourth columns show the revision in
          which the item last changed, and who changed it.</para>

        <para>None of the above invocations to <command>svn
            status</command> contact the repository, they work only
          locally by comparing the metadata in the
          <filename>.svn</filename> directory with the working
          copy.</para>
           
        <para>Finally, there is the <option>--show-updates</option>
          (<option>-u</option>) switch, which contacts the repository
          and adds information about things that are
          <firstterm>out-of-date</firstterm>:</para>
      
        <screen>
$ svn status --show-updates --verbose
M      *        44        23    sally     ./README
M               44        20    harry     ./bar.c
       *        44        35    harry     ./stuff/trout.c
D               44        19    ira       ./stuff/fish.c
A                0         ?     ?        ./stuff/things/bloo.h
        </screen>
           
        <para>Notice the two asterisks: if you were to run
          <command>svn update</command> at this point, you would
          receive changes to<filename>README</filename>
          and<filename>trout.c</filename>.  This tells you some very
          useful information&mdash;you'll need to update and get the
          server-changes on<filename>README</filename> before you
          commit, or the repository will reject your commit for being
          out-of-date.  (More on this subject later).</para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="svn-ch-3-sect-4.3.2">
        <title><command>svn diff</command></title>
           
        <para>Another way to examine your changes is with the
          <command>svn diff</command> command.  You can find out
          <emphasis>exactly</emphasis> how you've modified things by
          running <command>svn diff</command> with no arguments, which
          prints out file changes in unified diff format:</para>
        
        <screen>
$ svn diff
Index: ./bar.c
===================================================================
--- ./bar.c
+++ ./bar.c	Mon Jul 15 17:58:18 2002
@@ -1,7 +1,12 @@
+#include &lt;sys/types.h&gt;
+#include &lt;sys/stat.h&gt;
+#include &lt;unistd.h&gt;
+
+#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

int main(void) {
-  printf("Sixty-four slices of American Cheese...\n");
+  printf("Sixty-five slices of American Cheese...\n");
return 0;
}

Index: ./README
===================================================================
--- ./README
+++ ./README	Mon Jul 15 17:58:18 2002
@@ -193,3 +193,4 @@ 
+Note to self:  pick up laundry.

Index: ./stuff/fish.c
===================================================================
--- ./stuff/fish.c
+++ ./stuff/fish.c  Mon Jul 15 17:58:18 2002
-Welcome to the file known as 'fish'.
-Information on fish will be here soon.

Index: ./stuff/things/bloo.h
===================================================================
--- ./stuff/things/bloo.h
+++ ./stuff/things/bloo.h  Mon Jul 15 17:58:18 2002
+Here is a new file to describe
+things about bloo.
        </screen>
        
        <para>The <command>svn diff</command> command produces this
          output by comparing your working files against the cached
          <quote>pristine</quote> copies within the
          <filename>.svn</filename> area.  Files scheduled for
          addition are displayed as all added-text, and files
          scheduled for deletion are displayed as all deleted
          text.</para>

        <para>Output is displayed in <firstterm>unified diff
          format</firstterm>.  That is, removed lines are prefaced
          with a <literal>-</literal> and added lines are prefaced
          with a <literal>+</literal>.  <command>svn diff</command>
          also prints filename and offset information useful to the
          <command>patch</command> program, so you can generate
          <quote>patches</quote> by redirecting the diff output to a
          file:</para>

        <screen>
$ svn diff > patchfile
        </screen>

        <para>You could, for example, email the patchfile to another
          developer for review or testing prior to commit.</para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="svn-ch-3-sect-4.3.3">
        <title><command>svn revert</command></title>

        <para>Now suppose you see the above diff output, and realize
          that your changes to <filename>README</filename> are a
          mistake; perhaps you accidentally typed that text into the
          wrong file in your editor.</para>
      
        <para>This is a perfect opportunity to use <command>svn
          revert</command>.</para>
           
        <screen>
$ svn revert README
Reverted ./README
        </screen>
        
        <para>Subversion reverts the file to its pre-modified state by
          overwriting it with the cached <quote>pristine</quote> copy
          from the <filename>.svn</filename> area.  But also note that
          <command>svn revert</command> can undo
          <emphasis>any</emphasis> scheduled operations&mdash;for
          example, you might decide that you don't want to add a new
          file after all:</para>

        <screen>
$ svn status foo
?      foo

$ svn add foo
A         foo

$ svn revert foo
Reverted foo

$ svn status foo
?      foo
        </screen>

        <para>Or perhaps you mistakenly removed a file from version
          control:</para>

        <screen>
$ svn status README 
       README

$ svn delete README 
D         README

$ svn revert README
Reverted README

$ svn status README
       README
        </screen>

      </sect3>

      <sidebar>
          <title>Look Ma! No Network!</title>

        <para>All three of these commands (<command>svn
          status</command>, <command>svn diff</command>, and
          <command>svn revert</command>) can be used without any
          network access (except for the
          <option>--show-updates</option> (<option>-u</option>) switch
          to status).  This makes it easy to manage your
          changes-in-progress when you find yourself somewhere without
          a network connection (e.g. traveling on an airplane, riding
          on a commuter train, etc.).</para>

        <para>Subversion manages this by keeping private caches of
          pristine versions of each versioned file inside of the
          <filename>.svn</filename> administrative areas.  This allows
          Subversion to report&mdash;and revert&mdash;local
          modifications to those files <emphasis>without network
          access</emphasis>.  CVS keeps no such cache, and as a result
          has to use the network layer for practically everything.
          This cache (called the "text-base") also allows Subversion
          to, during a commit, send the user's local modifications to
          the server as a compressed delta against the pristine
          version.  Since at commit time CVS has only the user's
          edited version of a file, it has to send the
          <emphasis>entire file</emphasis> to the server in order to
          relay the local modifications.  At first glance, this might
          not seem too bad, but imagine the repercussions if try to
          commit a 1 line change to a 400MB file!</para>
    </sidebar>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="svn-ch-3-sect-4.4">
      <title>Resolving conflicts (Merging others' changes)</title>
           
      <para>We've already seen how <command>svn status -u</command>
          can predict conflicts.  Suppose you run <command>svn
          update</command> and some interesting things occur:</para>
      
      <screen>
$ svn update
U  ./INSTALL
G  ./README
C  ./bar.c
      </screen>
           
      <para>The <computeroutput>U</computeroutput> and
        <computeroutput>G</computeroutput> codes are no cause for
        concern; those files cleanly absorbed changes from the
        repository.  The files marked with
        <computeroutput>U</computeroutput> contained no local changes
        but were <computeroutput>U</computeroutput>pdated with changes
        from the repository.  The <computeroutput>G</computeroutput>
        stands for mer<computeroutput>G</computeroutput>ed, which
        means that the file had local changes to begin with, but the
        changes coming from the repository didn't overlap in any
        way.</para>
           
      <para>But the <computeroutput>C</computeroutput> stands for
        conflict.  This means that the changes from the server overlapped
        with your own, and now you have to manually choose between
        them.</para>
           
      <para>Whenever a conflict occurs, your Subversion client does
      the following:</para>
           
      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem>
          <para>Subversion prints a <computeroutput>C</computeroutput> during
            the update, and remembers that the file is
            <quote>conflicted.</quote></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Subversion places <firstterm>Conflict markers</firstterm> into the file, to visibly
           demonstrate the overlapping areas.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>For every conflicted file, Subversion places three
            extra files in your working copy:</para>

            <!-- ###TODO make this a varlist -->
            <!-- ###TODO sidebar about svn not screwing up your file. -->
            <itemizedlist>
              
              <listitem>
                <para><filename>filename.*.mine</filename> This is
                  your file as it existed in your working copy before
                  you updated your working copy&mdash;that is, without
                  conflict markers.  This file has your latest changes
                  in it and nothing else.</para>
              </listitem>
                  
              <listitem>
                <para><filename>filename.*.oldrevision</filename> This is
                  the file that was the BASE revision before you
                  updated your working copy.  That is, it the file
                  that you checked out before you made your latest
                  edits.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><filename>filename.*.newrevision</filename> This
                  is the file that your Subversion client just
                  received from the server when you updated your
                  working copy.  This file corresponds to the HEAD
                  revision of the repository.</para>
              </listitem>
              
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>Here<literal>*</literal> represents some random
              digits that Subversion chooses,
              <literal>oldrevision</literal> is the revision number of
              the file in your <filename>.svn</filename> directory,
              and <literal>newrevision</literal> is the revision
              number of the repository HEAD.
              </para>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>

      <para>For example, Sally makes changes to the file
        <filename>sandwich</filename> in the repository.  Harry has
        just changed the file in his working copy and checked it in.
        Sally updates her working copy before checking in and she gets
        a conflict:</para>
      
      <screen>
$ svn update
C  sandwich
Updated to revision 2.
$ ls -1
sandwich                       
sandwich.59528.00001.r2        
sandwich.59524.00001.r1
sandwich.59532.00001.mine
$
      </screen>
      <!-- ###TODO What happens if the revnum is gt 99999?-->
      
      <para>At this point, Subversion will <emphasis>not</emphasis>
        allow you to commit the file
        <filename>sandwich</filename>until the three temporary files
        are removed.</para>

      <screen>
$ svn ci --message "Add a few more things"
subversion/libsvn_client/commit.c:654: (apr_err=155015, src_err=0)
svn: A conflict in working copy obstructs the current operation
svn: Commit failed (details follow):
subversion/libsvn_client/commit_util.c:180: (apr_err=155015, src_err=0)
svn: Aborting commit: '/home/sally/svn-work/sandwich' remains in conflict.
      </screen>

      <para>If you get a conflict, you need to either (1) hand-merge
        the conflicted text (by examining and editing the conflict
        markers within the file), (2) copy one of the tmpfiles on top
        of your working file, or (3) run <command>svn revert
        &lt;filename&gt;</command> to throw away all of your local
        changes.</para>

<!-- ###TODO Talk more here about conflict markers and external diff
programs -->

      <screen>
$ cp sandwich.59532.00001.mine sandwich
      </screen>
      
      <para>Once you've resolved the conflict, you need to let
        Subversion know by removing the three temporary files.  (The
        <command>svn resolve</command> command, by the way, is a
        shortcut that does nothing but automatically remove the three
        temporary files for you.)  When those files are gone,
        Subversion no longer considers the file to be in a state of
        conflict anymore.</para>

      <screen>
$ svn resolve sandwich
Resolved conflicted state of sandwich
      </screen>

      <para>Now you're ready to check in your changes</para>
      
      <screen>
$ svn ci --message "Add a few more things"
Sending        sandwich
Transmitting file data .
Committed revision 3.
      </screen>

      <para>Note that<command>svn resolve</command>, unlike most of
        the other commands we've dealt with in this chapter, requires
        an argument.  In any case, you want to be careful and only run
        <command>svn resolve</command> when you're certain that you've
        fixed the conflict in your file&mdash;once the temporary files
        are removed, Subversion will even let you check in a file with
        conflict markers.</para>
      
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2 id="svn-ch-3-sect-4.5">
      <title>Commit your changes</title>
      
      <para>Finally!  Your edits are finished, you've merged all
        updates from the server, and you're ready to commit your
        changes to the repository.</para>
      
      <para>The <command>svn commit</command> command sends all (or,
           if you specify files or directories, some) of your changes
           to the repository.  When you commit a change, you need to
           supply a <firstterm>log message</firstterm>, describing
           your change.  Your log message will be attached
           to the new revision you create.  If your log message is
           brief, you may wish to supply it on the command line using
           the <option>--message</option> (or <option>-m</option>):</para>
           
      <screen>
$ svn commit --message "Corrected number of cheese slices."
Sending        sandwich
Transmitting file data .
Committed revision 3.
      </screen>
           
      <para>However, if you've been composing your log message as you
        work, you may want to tell Subversion to get the message from
        a file by passing the filename with the
        <option>--file</option> switch:</para>

      <screen>
svn ci --file logmsg 
Sending        sandwich
Transmitting file data .
Committed revision 4.
      </screen>

      <para>If you fail to specify either the <option>--message</option>
        or <option>--file</option> switch, then Subversion will
        automatically launch your favorite editor (As defined in the
        environment variable <literal>$EDITOR</literal>) for composing
        a log message.</para>
           
      <para>The repository doesn't know or care if your changes make
        any sense as a whole; it only checks to make sure that nobody
        else has changed any of the same files that you did when you
        weren't looking.  If somebody <emphasis>has</emphasis> done
        that, the entire commit will fail with a message informing you
        that one or more of your files is out-of-date:</para>

<screen>
$ svn commit --message "Add another rule"
Sending        rules.txt
subversion/libsvn_client/commit.c:655: (apr_err=160028, src_err=0)
svn: Transaction is out of date
svn: Commit failed (details follow):
subversion/libsvn_repos/commit.c:112: (apr_err=160028, src_err=0)
svn: out of date: `rules.txt' in txn `g'
$
</screen>

      <para>At this point, you need to run <command>svn
        update</command>, deal with any merges or conflicts that
        result, and attempt your commit again.</para>
           
      <para>That covers the basic work cycle for using Subversion.
        There are many other features in Subversion that you can use
        to manage your repository and working copy, but you can get by
        quite easily using only the commands that we've discussed so
        far in this chapter.</para>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ======================== SECTION 5 ============================== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn-ch-3-sect-5">
    <title>Examining History</title>

    <para>As we mentioned earlier, the repository is like a time
      machine.  It keeps a record of every revision ever committed,
      and allows you to explore this history by examining previous
      versions of files and directories as well as the metadata that
      accompanies them.  With a single Subversion command, you can
      check out (or restore an existing working copy) the repository
      exactly as it was at any date or revision number in the past.
      However, sometimes you just want to <emphasis>peer
      into</emphasis> the past instead of <emphasis>going
      into</emphasis> the past.</para>
           
    <para>There are several commands that can provide you with
      historical data from the repository.  <command>svn log</command>
      shows you broad information: log messages attached to revisions,
      and which paths changed in each revision.  <command>svn
      diff</command>, on the other hand, can show you the specific
      details of how a file changed over time.  Finally, <command>svn
      cat</command> can be used to retrieve any file as it existed in
      a particular revision number and display it on your screen.</para>

    <sect2 id="svn-ch-3-sect-5.1">
      <title><command>svn log</command></title>

      <para>To find out information about the history of a file or
        directory, use the <command>svn log</command>
        command. <command>svn log</command> will provide you with a
        record of who made changes to a file or directory, at what
        revision it changed, the time and date of that revision, and,
        if it was provided, the log message that accompanied the
        commit.</para>
           
      <screen>
$ svn log
------------------------------------------------------------------------
rev 3:  sally | Mon, 15 Jul 2002 18:03:46 -0500 | 1 line

Added include lines and corrected # of cheese slices.
------------------------------------------------------------------------
rev 2:  harry | Mon, 15 Jul 2002 17:47:57 -0500 | 1 line

Added main() methods.
------------------------------------------------------------------------
rev 1:  sally | Mon, 15 Jul 2002 17:40:08 -0500 | 2 lines

Initial import
------------------------------------------------------------------------
      </screen>
           
      <para>Note that the log messages are printed in
        <emphasis>reverse chronological order</emphasis> by default.
        If you wish to see a different range of revisions in a
        particular order, or just a single revision, pass the
        <option>--revision</option> (<option>-r</option>)
        switch:</para>
           
      <screen>
$ svn log --revision 5:19
&hellip; # shows logs 5 through 19 in chronological order
$ svn log -r 19:5
&hellip; # shows logs 5 through 19 in reverse order
$ svn log -r 8
&hellip;
      </screen>
        
      <para>You can also examine the log history of a single file or directory.
      For example:</para>
           
      <screen>
$ svn log foo.c
&hellip;
$ svn log http://foo.com/svn/trunk/code/foo.c
&hellip;
      </screen>
           
      <para>These will display log messages <emphasis>only</emphasis>
        for those revisions in which the working file (or URL)
        changed.</para>
           
      <para>If you want even more information about a file or
        directory, <command>svn log</command> also takes a
        <option>--verbose</option> (<option>-v</option>) switch.
        Because Subversion allows you to move and copy files and
        directories, it is important to be able to track path changes
        in the filesystem, so in verbose mode, <command>svn
        log</command> will include a list of
        <firstterm>changed-paths</firstterm> in a revision in its
        output:</para>

      <screen>
$ svn log -r 8 -v
------------------------------------------------------------------------
rev 8:  sally | 2002-07-14 08:15:29 -0500 | 1 line
Changed paths:
U /trunk/code/foo.c
U /trunk/code/bar.h
A /trunk/code/doc/README

Frozzled the sub-space winch.

------------------------------------------------------------------------
      </screen>
           
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="svn-ch-3-sect-5.2">
      <title>svn diff</title>

      <para>We've already seen <command>svn diff</command>
        above&mdash;it displays file differences in unified diff
        format; it was used to show the local modifications made to
        our working copy before committing to the repository.</para>
      
      <para>In fact, it turns out that there are
        <emphasis>three</emphasis> distinct uses of <command>svn
          diff</command>:</para>

      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem>
          <para>Examine local changes</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Compare your working copy to the repository</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Compare repository to repository</para>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
      
      <sect3 id="svn-ch-3-sect-5.2.1">
        <title>Examining local changes</title>

        <para>As we saw above, invoking <command>svn diff</command>
          with no switches will compare your working files to the
          cached <quote>pristine</quote> copies in
          the<filename>.svn</filename> area:</para>
        
        <screen>
$ svn diff
Index: rules.txt
===================================================================
--- rules.txt	(revision 3)
+++ rules.txt	(working copy)
@@ -1,4 +1,5 @@
 Be kind to others
 Freedom = Responsibility
 Everything in moderation
-Chew with your mouth closed
+Chew with your mouth closed
+Listen when others are speaking
$
        </screen>
        
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="svn-ch-3-sect-5.2.2">
        <title>Comparing working copy to repository</title>

        <para>If a single <option>--revision</option>
          (<option>-r</option>) number is passed, then your
          working copy is compared to the specified revision in the
          repository.</para>
          
        <screen>
$ svn diff --revision 3 rules.txt 
Index: rules.txt
===================================================================
--- rules.txt	(revision 3)
+++ rules.txt	(working copy)
@@ -1,4 +1,5 @@
 Be kind to others
 Freedom = Responsibility
 Everything in moderation
-Chew with your mouth closed
+Chew with your mouth closed
+Listen when others are speaking
$
        </screen>
          
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="svn-ch-3-sect-5.2.3">
        <title>Comparing repository to repository</title>
        
        <para>If two revision numbers, separated by a colon, are
          passed via <option>--revision</option>
          (<option>-r</option>), then the two revisions are directly
          compared.</para>
          
        <screen>
$ svn diff --revision 2:3 rules.txt 
Index: rules.txt
===================================================================
--- rules.txt	(revision 2)
+++ rules.txt	(revision 3)
@@ -1,4 +1,4 @@
 Be kind to others
-Freedom = Chocolate Ice Cream
+Freedom = Responsibility
 Everything in moderation
 Chew with your mouth closed 
$
        </screen>
          
        <para>Not only can you use <command>svn diff</command> to
           compare files in your working copy to the repository, but
           if you supply a URL argument, you can examine the
           differences between items in the repository without even
           having a working copy.  This is especially useful if you
           wish to inspect changes in a file when you don't have a
           working copy on your local machine:</para>
           
        <screen>
$ svn diff --revision 4:5 http://svn.red-bean.com/repos/example/trunk/text/rules.txt
&hellip;
$
        </screen>

      </sect3>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="svn-ch-3-sect-5.3">
      <title><command>svn cat</command></title>

      <para>If you want to examine an earlier version of a file and
        not necessarily the differences between two files, you can use
        <command>svn cat</command>:</para>

      <screen>
$ svn cat --revision 2 rules.txt 
Be kind to others
Freedom = Chocolate Ice Cream
Everything in moderation
Chew with your mouth closed
$
      </screen>

      <para>You can also redirect the output directly into a
        file:</para>

      <screen>
$ svn cat --revision 2 rules.txt > rules.txt.v2
$
      </screen>

      <para>Now you're probably wondering why we don't just use
        <command>svn update --revision</command> to update the file to
        the older revision.  Well, there are several reasons that we
        might prefer to use <command>svn cat</command>.</para>

      <para>First, you may want to see the differences between 2
        revisions of a file using an external diff program (perhaps a
        graphical one, or perhaps your file is in such a format that
        the output ofunified diff is nonsensical).  In this case,
        you'll need to grab a copy of the old revision, redirect it to
        a file, and pass both that and the file in your working copy
        to your external diff program.</para>

      <para>Second, you may have local changes to the file and don't
        want to lose them.</para>

      <para>Finally, sometimes it's easier to look at an older
        revision in its entirety as opposed to just the differences
        between it and another revision.</para>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ======================== SECTION 6 ============================== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn-ch-3-sect-6">
    <title>Revision <quote>Numbers</quote></title>

    <para>As you've probably noticed by now, many Subversion commands
      can take a <option>--revision</option> (<option>-r</option>)
      switch.  Here we describe some special ways to specify
      revisions.</para>

    <para>The Subversion client understands a number of
      <firstterm>revision keywords</firstterm>.  These keywords can be
      used instead of integer arguments to the
      <option>--revision</option> switch, and are resolved into
      specific revision numbers by Subversion:</para>
    
    <variablelist>
      
      <varlistentry>
        <term>HEAD</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The latest revision in the repository.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>BASE</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The <quote>pristine</quote> revision of an item in a
            working copy.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>COMMITTED</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The last revision in which an item changed.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>PREV</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The revision just <emphasis>before</emphasis> the last
            revision in which an item changed.  (Technically,
            COMMITTED - 1).</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

    <para>Here are some examples of revision keywords in
      action:</para>

    <screen>
$ svn diff --revision PREV:COMMITTED foo.c
# shows the last change committed to foo.c

$ svn log --revision HEAD
# shows log message for the latest repository commit

$ svn diff --revision HEAD
# compares your working file (with local mods) to the latest version
# in the repository.

$ svn diff --revision BASE:HEAD foo.c
# compares your <quote>pristine</quote> foo.c (no local mods) with the 
# latest version in the repository

$ svn log --revision BASE:HEAD
# shows all commit logs since you last updated

$ svn update --revision PREV foo.c
# rewinds the last change on foo.c.
# (foo.c's working revision is decreased.)
    </screen>

    <para>These keywords may not seem terribly important, but they do
      allow you to perform many common (and helpful) operations
      without having to look up specific revision numbers or remember
      the exact revision of your working copy.</para>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ======================== SECTION 7 ============================== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn-ch-3-sect-7">
    <title>Other Commands</title>

    <sect2 id="svn-ch-3-sect-7.1">
      <title><command>svn cleanup</command></title>

      <para>When Subversion modifies your working copy (or any
        information within <filename>.svn</filename>), it tries to do
        so as safely as possible.  Before changing anything, it writes
        its intentions to a logfile, executes the commands in the
        logfile, then removes the logfile (This is similar in design
        to a journaled filesystem).  If a Subversion operation is
        interrupted (If you hit Control-C, or if the machine crashes,
        for example), the logfiles remain on disk.  By re-executing
        the logfiles, Subversion can complete the previously started
        operation, and your working copy can get itself back into a
        consistent state.</para>

      <para>And this is exactly what <command>svn cleanup</command>
        does: it searches your working copy and runs any leftover
        logs, removing locks in the process.  If Subversion ever tells
        you that some part of your working copy is
        <quote>locked</quote>, then this is the command that you
        should run.  Also, <command>svn status</command> will display
        an <literal>L</literal> next to locked items:</para>

      <screen>
$ svn status
  L    ./somedir
M      ./somedir/foo.c 

$ svn cleanup
$ svn status
M      ./somedir/foo.c
      </screen>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="svn-ch-3-sect-7.2">
      <title><command>svn info</command></title>

      <para>In general, we try to discourage you from directly reading
        the <filename>.svn/entries</filename> file used to track items
        in a Subversion working copy.  Instead, you can get tons of
        information about an item in your working copy by using the
        <command>svn info</command> command to display most of the
        tracked information:</para>

      <screen>
$ svn info rules.txt
Path: rules.txt
Name: rules.txt
Url: http://svn.red-bean.com/repos/example/trunk/text/rules.txt
Revision: 8
Node Kind: file
Schedule: normal
Last Changed Author: harry
Last Changed Rev: 7
Last Changed Date: 2002-11-15 23:03:54 -0500 (Fri, 15 Nov 2002)
Text Last Updated: 2002-11-16 08:48:04 -0500 (Sat, 16 Nov 2002)
Properties Last Updated: 2002-11-16 08:48:03 -0500 (Sat, 16 Nov 2002)
Checksum: 8sfaU+5dqyOgkhuSdyxGrQ==
      </screen>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="svn-ch-3-sect-7.3">
      <title><command>svn import</command></title>

      <para>The import command is a quick way to move an unversioned
        tree of files into a repository.</para>

      <para>There are two ways to use this command:</para>

      <screen>
$ svnadmin create /usr/local/svn/newrepos
$ svn import file:///usr/local/svn/newrepos mytree
Adding  mytree/foo.c
Adding  mytree/bar.c
Adding  mytree/subdir
Adding  mytree/subdir/quux.h
Transmitting file data....
Committed revision 1.
      </screen>

      <para>The above example places the contents of directory
        <filename>mytree</filename> directly into the root of the
        repository:</para>

      <screen>
/foo.c
/bar.c
/subdir
/subdir/quux.h
      </screen>

      <para>If you give <command>svn import</command> a third
        argument, it will use the argument as the name of a new
        subdirectory to create within the URL.</para>

      <screen>
$ svnadmin create /usr/local/svn/newrepos
$ svn import file:///usr/local/svn/newrepos mytree fooproject
Adding  mytree/foo.c
Adding  mytree/bar.c
Adding  mytree/subdir
Adding  mytree/subdir/quux.h
Transmitting file data....
Committed revision 1.
      </screen>

      <para>The repository would now look like this:</para>

      <screen>
/fooproject/foo.c
/fooproject/bar.c
/fooproject/subdir
/fooproject/subdir/quux.h
      </screen>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="svn-ch-3-sect-7.4">
      <title><command>svn export</command></title>

      <para>The export command is a quick way to create an unversioned
        tree of files from a repository directory&mdash;a tree that
        looks like a typical working copy, but doesn't contain the
        <filename>.svn</filename> directories:</para>

      <screen>
$ svn export file:///usr/local/svn/newrepos/fooproject
A  fooproject/foo.c
A  fooproject/bar.c
A  fooproject/subdir
A  fooproject/subdir/quux.h
Checked out revision 3.
      </screen>

      <para>The resulting directory will not contain any
        <filename>.svn</filename> administrative areas, and all
        property metadata will be lost.  (Hint: don't use this
        technique for backing up; it's probably better for rolling
        source distributions.)</para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="svn-ch-3-sect-7.5">
      <title><command>svn list</command></title>

      <para>The <command>svn list</command> command shows you what
        files are in a repository directory without actually
        downloading the files to your local machine:</para>
      
      <screen>
$ svn list http://svn.collab.net/repos/svn
README
branches/
clients/
tags/
trunk/
      </screen>

      <para>If you want a more detailed listing, pass the
        <option>--verbose</option> (<option>-v</option>) flag to get
        output like this.</para>

      <screen>
$ svn list --verbose http://svn.collab.net/repos/svn
_    2755   kfogel     1331 Jul 28 02:07 README
_    2773  sussman        0 Jul 29 15:07 branches/
_    2769 cmpilato        0 Jul 29 12:07 clients/
_    2698   rooneg        0 Jul 24 18:07 tags/
_    2785    brane        0 Jul 29 19:07 trunk/
      </screen>

      <para>The columns tell you if a file has any properties
        (<quote>P</quote> if it does, <quote>_</quote> if it doesn't),
        the revision it was last updated at, the user who last updated
        it, the size if it is a file, the date it was last updated,
        and the item's name.</para>
 
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="svn-ch-3-sect-7.6">
      <title><command>svn mkdir</command></title>

      <para>This is another convenience command, and it has two
        uses.</para>

      <para>First, it can be used to simultaneously create a new working copy
        directory and schedule it for addition:</para>
      
      <screen>
$ svn mkdir new-dir
A     new-dir
      </screen>

      <para>Or, it can be used to instantly create a directory in a
        repository (no working copy needed):</para>

      <screen>
$ svn mkdir file:///usr/local/svn/newrepos/branches --message "made new dir"
Committed revision 1123.
      </screen>

      <para>Again, this is a form of immediate commit, so some sort of
        log message is required.</para>

    </sect2>

    <para>Now we've covered all of the Subversion client commands with
      the exception of those dealing with branching and merging (see
      <xref linkend="svn-ch-4"/>) and properties (see <xref
      linkend="svn-ch-6-sect-2"/>).  However, you may want to take a
      moment to skim through <xref linkend="svn-ch-8"/> to get an idea
      of the many different ways that you can use the commands that we
      covered above.</para>

  </sect1>

</chapter>

<!--
local variables: 
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->

