<chapter id="svn-ch-5">
<title>Repository Administration</title>

  <simplesect>

    <para>The Subversion repository is the central storehouse of
      versioned data for any number of projects.  As such, it becomes
      an obvious candidate for all the love and attention an
      administrator can offer.  While the repository is generally a
      low-maintenance item, it is important to understand how to
      properly configure and care for it so that potential problems
      are avoided, and actual problems safely resolved.  In this
      chapter, we'll discuss:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>repository creation and configuration.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>repository networking.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>repository maintenance, including the use of the
          <command>svnlook</command> and <command>svnadmin</command>
          tools provided with Subversion.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>repository layout: suggestions for how to arrange the
          versioned data in your repository.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>common questions and mistakes regarding repositories.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>If you plan to access a Subversion repository only in the
      role of a user whose data is under version control (that is, via
      a Subversion client), you can skip this chapter altogether.
      However, if you are, or wish to become, a Subversion repository
      administrator,
      <footnote>
        <para>This may sound really prestigious and lofty, but we're
          just talking about anyone who is interested in that
          mysterious realm beyond the working copy where everyone's
          data hangs out.</para>
      </footnote>
      you should definitely pay attention to this chapter.</para>

    <para>Of course, one cannot administer a repository unless one has
      a repository to administer.</para>

  </simplesect>

  <!-- ******************************************************************* -->
  <!-- *** SECTION 1:  REPOSITORY CREATION AND CONFIGURATION           *** -->
  <!-- ******************************************************************* -->
  <sect1 id="svn-ch-5-sect-1">
    <title>Repository Creation and Configuration</title>

    <para>Creating a Subversion repository is an incredibly simple
      task.  The <command>svnadmin</command> utility, provided with
      Subversion, has a subcommand for doing just that.  To create a
      new repository, just run:</para>
          
    <screen>
$ svnadmin create path/to/repos
</screen>
          
    <para>This creates a new repository in the directory
      <filename>path/to/repos</filename>.  This new repository begins
      life at revision 0, which is defined to consist of nothing but
      the top-level root (<filename>/</filename>) filesystem
      directory.  Initially, revision 0 also has a single revision
      property, <literal>svn:date</literal>, set to the time at which
      the repository was created.</para>
          
    <para>You may have noticed that the path argument to
      <command>svnadmin</command> was just a regular filesystem path
      and not a URL like the <command>svn</command> client program
      uses when referring to repositories.  Both
      <command>svnadmin</command> and <command>svnlook</command> are
      considered server-side utilities&mdash;they are used on the
      machine where the repository resides to examine or modify
      aspects of the repository, and are in fact unable to perform
      tasks across a network.  A common mistake made by Subversion
      newcomers is trying to pass URLs (even "local"
      <literal>file:</literal> ones) to these two programs.</para>

    <para>So, after you've run the <command>svnadmin create</command>
      command, you have a shiny new Subversion repository in its own
      directory.  Let's take a peek at what is actually created inside
      that subdirectory.</para>
            
    <screen>
$ ls repos
conf/  dav/  db/  format  hooks/  locks/  README
</screen>
      
    <para>As you can see, immediately inside the repository directory
      is a collection of mostly subdirectories.  As in other areas of
      the Subversion design, modularity is given high regard, and
      hierarchical organization is preferred to cluttered chaos.  The
      following is a brief description of all of the items you see in
      your new repository directory:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>conf</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Currently unused, repository configuration files will
            go in this directory someday.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
        <term>dav</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A directory provided to Apache and mod_dav_svn for
            their private housekeeping data.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
        <term>db</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The main Berkeley DB environment, full of DB tables
            that comprise the data store for Subversion's filesystem
            (where all of your versioned data resides).</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
        <term>format</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A file whose contents are a single integer value that
            dictates the version number of the repository layout.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
        <term>hooks</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A directory full of hook script templates (and hook
            scripts themselves, once you've installed some).</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
        <term>locks</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A directory for Subversion's repository locking
            data, used for tracking accessors to the repository.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
        <term>README</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A file which merely informs its readers that they
            are looking at a Subversion repository.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
      
    <para>In general, you'll not want to tamper with most of the items
      in your repository, at least not <quote>by hand</quote>.  The
      <command>svnadmin</command> tool should be sufficient for any
      changes necessary to your repository, or you can look to
      third-party tools (such as Berkeley DB's tool suite) for
      tweaking relevant subsections of the repository.  Some
      exceptions exist, though, and we'll cover those here.</para>

    <!-- ***************************************************************** -->
    <sect2 id="svn-ch-5-sect-1.1">
      <title>Hook scripts</title>

      <para>A <firstterm>hook</firstterm> is a program triggered by
        some repository event, such as the creation of a new revision
        or the modification of an unversioned property.  Each hook is
        handed enough information to tell what that event is, what
        target(s) it's operating on, and the username of the person
        who triggered the event.  Depending on the hook's output or
        return status, the hook program may continue the action, stop
        it, or suspend it in some way.</para>
            
      <para>The <filename>hooks</filename> subdirectory is, by
        default, filled with templates for various repository
        hooks.</para>
            
      <screen>
$ ls repos/hooks/
post-commit.tmpl          pre-revprop-change.tmpl  write-sentinels.tmpl
post-revprop-change.tmpl  read-sentinels.tmpl
pre-commit.tmpl           start-commit.tmpl
</screen>
            
      <para>There is one template for each hook that the Subversion
        repository implements, and by examining the contents of those
        template scripts, you can see what triggers each such script
        to run and what data is passed to that script.  Also present
        in many of these templates are examples of how one might use
        that script, in conjunction with other Subversion-supplied
        programs, to perform common useful tasks.  To actually install
        a working hook, you need only place some executable program or
        script into the <filename>repos/hooks</filename> directory
        which can be executed as the name (like
        <command>start-commit</command> or
        <command>post-commit</command>) of the hook.</para>

      <para>On Unix platforms, this means supplying a script or
        program (which could be a shell script, a Python program, a
        compiled C binary, or any number of other things) named
        exactly like the name of the hook.  Of course, the template
        files are present for more than just informational
        purposes&mdash;the easiest way to install a hook on Unix
        platforms is to simply copy the appropriate template file to a
        new file that lacks the <literal>.tmpl</literal> extension,
        customize the hook's contents, and ensure that the script is
        executable.  Windows, however, uses file extensions to
        determine whether or not a program is executable, so you would
        need to supply a program whose basename is the name of the
        hook, and whose extension is one of the special extensions
        recognized by Windows for executable programs, such as
        <filename>.exe</filename> or <filename>.com</filename> for
        programs, and <filename>.bat</filename> for batch
        files.</para>
          
      <para>Currently there are five true hooks implemented by the
        Subversion repository.</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><filename>start-commit</filename></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>This is run before the commit transaction is even
              created.  It is typically used to decide if the user has
              commit privileges at all.  The repository passes two
              arguments to this program: the path to the repository,
              and username which is attempting the commit.  If the
              program returns a non-zero exit value, the commit is
              stopped before the transaction is even created.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
            
        <varlistentry>
          <term><filename>pre-commit</filename></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>This is run when the transaction is complete, but
              before it is committed.  Typically, this hook is used to
              protect against commits that are disallowed due to
              content or location (for example, your site might
              require that all commits to a certain branch include a
              ticket number from the bug tracker, or that the incoming
              log message is non-empty).  The repository passes two
              arguments to this program: the path to the repository,
              and the name of the transaction being committed.  If the
              program returns a non-zero exit value, the commit is
              aborted and transaction is removed.</para>

            <para>The Subversion distribution includes a
              <command>commit-access-control.pl</command> script
              (located in the <filename>tools/hook-scripts</filename>
              directory of the Subversion source tree) that can be
              called from <command>pre-commit</command> to implement
              fine-grained access control.  At this time, this is the
              only method by which users can implement finer-grained
              access control beyond what
              <filename>httpd.conf</filename> offers.  In a future
              version of Subversion, we plan to implement ACLs
              directly in the filesystem.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><filename>post-commit</filename></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>This is run after the transaction is committed, and
              a new revision is created.  Most people use this hook to
              send out descriptive emails about the commit or to make
              a backup of the repository.  The repository passes two
              arguments to this program: the path to the repository,
              and the new revision number that was created.  The exit
              code of the program is ignored.</para>
                
            <para>The Subversion distribution includes a
              <command>commit-email.pl</command> script (located in
              the <filename>tools/hook-scripts/</filename> directory
              of the Subversion source tree) that can be used to send
              email with (and/or append to a log file) a description
              of a given commit.  This mail contains a list of the
              paths that were changed, the log message attached to the
              commit, the author and date of the commit, as well as a
              GNU diff-style display of the changes made to the
              various versioned files as part of the commit.</para>

            <para>Another useful tool provided by Subversion is the
              <command>hot-backup.py</command> script (located in the
              <filename>tools/backup/</filename> directory of the
              Subversion source tree).  This script performs hot
              backups of your Subversion repository (a feature
              supported by the Berkeley DB database back-end), and can
              be used to make a per-commit snapshot of your repository
              for archival or emergency recovery purposes.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><filename>pre-revprop-change</filename></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Because Subversion's revision properties are not
              versioned, making modifications to such a property (for
              example, the <literal>svn:log</literal> commit message
              property) will overwrite the previous value of that
              property forever.  Since data can be potentially lost
              here, Subversion supplies this hook (and its
              counterpart, <filename>post-revprop-change</filename>)
              so that repository administrators can keep records of
              changes to these items using some external means if
              they so desire.</para>

            <para>This hook runs just before such a modification is
              made to the repository.  The repository passes four
              arguments to this hook: the path to the repository, the
              revision on which the to-be-modified property exists, the
              authenticated username of the person making the change,
              and name of the property itself.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><filename>pre-revprop-change</filename></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>As mentioned earlier, this hook is the counterpart
              of <filename>pre-revprop-change</filename> hook.  In
              fact, for the sake of paranoia this script will not run
              unless the <filename>pre-revprop-change</filename> hook
              exists.  When both of these hooks are present, the
              <filename>post-revprop-change</filename> hook runs just
              after a revision property has been changed, and is
              typically used to send an email containing the new value
              of the changed property.  The repository passes four
              arguments to this hook: the path to the repository, the
              revision on which the property exists, the authenticated
              username of the person making the change, and name of
              the property itself.</para>

            <para>The Subversion distribution includes a
              <command>propchange-email.pl</command> script (located
              in the <filename>tools/hook-scripts/</filename>
              directory of the Subversion source tree) that can be
              used to send email with (and/or append to a log file)
              the details of a revision property change.  This mail
              contains the revision and name of the changed property,
              the user who made the change, and the new property
              value.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <sidebar>
        <title>Sentinels, Those <quote>Other</quote> Hooks</title>

        <para>In addition to the hook scripts, Subversion has
          templates for two other special event handlers&mdash;the
          <filename>read-sentinels</filename> and
          <filename>write-sentinels</filename>.  These special
          programs, called <firstterm>sentinels</firstterm>, are
          intended to be daemon-like applications which are started at
          the beginning of a user's operation, and which receive
          multiple event notifications of a single type over the
          course of that operation.  Depending on the sentinel's
          responses to each of these notifications, Subversion may
          stop or otherwise modify the operation.  Fortunately for
          today's Subversion repository administrators, these
          sentinels can be ignored, since support for them is not yet
          implemented in Subversion itself!</para>
      </sidebar>
            
      <para>Subversion will attempt to execute hooks as the same user
        who owns the Subversion repository process.  In most cases,
        the repository is being accessed via Apache HTTP server and
        mod_dav_svn, so this user is the same user that Apache runs
        as.  The hooks themselves will need to be configured with
        OS-level permissions that allow that user to execute them.
        Also, this means that any file or programs (including the
        Subversion repository itself) accessed directly or indirectly
        by the hook will be accessed as the same user.  In other
        words, be alert to potential permission-related problems that
        could prevent the hook from performing the tasks you've
        written it to perform.</para>

    </sect2>

    <!-- ***************************************************************** -->
    <sect2 id="svn-ch-5-sect-1.2">
      <title>Berkeley DB configuration</title>

      <para>The Berkeley DB environment has it own set of default
        configuration values for things like the number of locks
        allowed to be taken out at any given time, or the size
        cutoff for Berkeley's journaling log file, etc.
        Subversion's filesystem code additionally chooses default
        values for some of the Berkeley DB configuration options.
        However, sometimes your particular repository, with its
        unique collection of data and access patterns, might require
        a different set of configuration option values.</para>

     <para>The folks at Sleepycat (the producers of Berkeley DB)
        understand that different databases have different
        requirements, and so they have provided a mechanism for
        runtime overriding of many of the configuration values for the
        Berkeley DB environment.  Berkeley checks for the presence of
        a file named <filename>DB_CONFIG</filename> in each
        environment directory, and parses the options found in that
        file for use with that particular Berkeley environment.</para>

     <para>The Berkeley configuration overrides file for your
        repository is located in the <filename>db</filename>
        environment directory, at
        <filename>repos/db/DB_CONFIG</filename>.  Subversion itself
        creates this file when it creates the rest of the repository.
        The file initially contains some default options, as well as
        pointers to the Berkeley DB online documentation so you can
        read about what those options do.  Of course, you are free to
        add any of the supported Berkeley DB options to your
        <filename>DB_CONFIG</filename> file.  Just be aware that while
        Subversion never attempts to read or interpret the contents of
        the file, and makes no use of the option settings in it,
        you'll want to avoid any configuration changes that may cause
        Berkeley DB to behave in a fashion that is unexpected by the
        rest of the Subversion code.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ******************************************************************* -->
  <!-- *** SECTION 2:  REPOSITORY MAINTENANCE                          *** -->
  <!-- ******************************************************************* -->

  <sect1 id="svn-ch-5-sect-2">
    <title>Repository Maintenance</title>

    <!-- ***************************************************************** -->
    <sect2 id="svn-ch-5-sect-2.1">
      <title>Understanding Transactions and Revisions</title>
        
      <para>A Subversion repository is essentially a sequence of
        directory trees.  Each tree is a snapshot of how the files and
        directories versioned in your repository looked at various
        points in time.  These snapshots are created as a result of
        client operations, and are called revisions.</para>

      <para>Every revision begins life as a transaction tree.  When
        doing a commit, a client builds a Subversion transaction that
        mirrors their local changes (plus any additional changes that
        might have been made to the repository since the beginning of
        the client's commit process), and then instructs the
        repository to store that tree as the next snapshot in the
        sequence.  If the commit succeeds, the transaction is
        effectively promoted into a new revision tree, and is assigned
        a new revision number.  If the commit fails for some reason,
        the transaction is destroyed and the client is informed of the
        failure.</para>
            
      <para>At the moment, updates work in a similar way.  The client
        builds a temporary transaction tree that mimics the state of
        the working copy.  The repository then compares that
        transaction tree with the revision tree at the request
        revision (usually the most recent, or <quote>youngest</quote>
        tree), and sends back information that informs the client
        about what changes are needed to transform their working copy
        into a replica of that revision tree.  After the update
        completes, the temporary transaction is deleted.</para>
          
      <para>The use of transaction trees is the only way to make
        permanent changes to repository's versioned filesystem.
        However, it's important to understand that the lifetime of a
        transaction is completely flexible.  In the case of updates,
        transactions are temporary trees that are immediately
        destroyed.  In the case of commits, transactions are
        transformed into permanent revisions (or aborted if the commit
        fails).  In the case of an error or bug, it's possible that a
        transaction can be accidentally left lying around in the
        repository (not really affecting anything, but still taking up
        space).</para>

     <para>In theory, someday whole workflow applications might
        revolve around more fine-grained control of transaction
        lifetime.  It is feasible to imagine a system whereby each
        transaction slated to become a revision is left in stasis well
        after the client finishes describing its changes to
        repository.  This would enable each new commit to be reviewed
        by someone else, perhaps a manager or engineering QA team, who
        can choose to promote the transaction into a revision, or
        abort it.</para>
            
      <para>You might at this point be wondering what all of this has
        to do with repository administration.  The answer is simple:
        if you're administering a Subversion repository, you're going
        to have to examine revisions and transactions.  It's part of
        monitoring the health of, and tracking changes to, your
        repository.</para>
            
    </sect2>

    <!-- ***************************************************************** -->
    <sect2 id="svn-ch-5-sect-2.2">
      <title>An Administrator's Toolkit</title>

      <sect3 id="svn-ch-5-sect-2.2.1">
        <title>svnlook</title>
            
        <para><command>svnlook</command> is a tool provided by
          Subversion for examining the various revisions and
          transactions in a repository.  No part of this program
          attempts to change the repository&mdash;it's a
          <quote>read-only</quote> tool.  <command>svnlook</command>
          is typically used by the repository hooks for reporting
          the changes that are about to be committed (in the case of
          the <command>pre-commit</command> hook) or that were just
          committed (in the case of the <command>post-commit</command>
          hook) to the repository.  Also, a repository administrator
          may find himself using this tool for diagnostic
          purposes.</para>
            
        <para><command>svnlook</command> has a straightforward
          syntax:</para>
            
        <screen>
$ svnlook help
general usage: svnlook SUBCOMMAND REPOS_PATH [ARGS &amp; OPTIONS ...]
Note: any subcommand which takes the '--revision' and '--transaction'
      options will, if invoked without one of those options, act on
      the repository's youngest revision.
Type "svnlook help &lt;subcommand&gt;" for help on a specific subcommand.
&hellip;
</screen>

        <para>Nearly every one of <command>svnlook</command>'s
          subcommands can operate on either a revision or a
          transaction tree, printing information about the tree
          itself, or how it differs from the previous revision of the
          repository.  You use the <option>--revision</option> and
          <option>--transaction</option> options to specify which
          revision or transaction, respectively, to examine.  Note
          that while revision numbers appear as natural numbers,
          transaction names are alphanumeric strings.  Keep in mind
          that the filesystem only allows browsing of uncommitted
          transactions (transactions that have not resulted in a new
          revision).  Most repositories will have no such
          transactions, because transactions are usually either
          committed (which disqualifies them from viewing) or aborted
          and removed.</para>

        <para>In the absence of both the <option>--revision</option>
          and <option>--transaction</option> options,
          <command>svnlook</command> will examine the youngest (or
          <quote>HEAD</quote>) revision in the repository.  So the
          following two commands do exactly the same thing when 19 is
          the youngest revision in the repository located at
          <filename>/path/to/repos</filename>:</para>

        <screen>
$ svnlook info /path/to/repos
$ svnlook info /path/to/repos --revision 19
</screen>

        <para>The only exception to these rules about subcommands is
          the <command>svnlook youngest</command> subcommand, which
          takes no options, and simply prints out the HEAD revision
          number.</para>

        <screen>
$ svnlook youngest /path/to/repos
19
</screen>
            
        <para>Output from <command>svnlook</command> is designed to be
          both human- and machine-parsable.  Take as an example the output
          of the <literal>info</literal> subcommand:</para>

        <screen>
$ svnlook info path/to/repos
sally
2002-11-04 09:29:13 -0600 (Mon, 04 Nov 2002)
27
Added the usual
Greek tree.
</screen>

        <para>The output of the <literal>info</literal> subcommand is
          defined as:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The author, followed by a newline.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The date, followed by a newline.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The number of characters in the log message,
              followed by a newline.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The log message itself, followed by a newline.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>This output is human-readable, meaning items like the
          datestamp are displayed using a textual representation
          instead of something more obscure (such as the number of
          nanoseconds since the Tasty Freeze guy drove by).  But this
          output is also machine-parsable&mdash;because the log
          message can contain multiple lines and be unbounded in
          length, <command>svnlook</command> provides the length of
          that message before the message itself.  This allows scripts
          and other wrappers around this command to make intelligent
          decisions about the log message, such as how much memory to
          allocate for the message, or at least how many bytes to skip
          in the event that this output is not the last bit of data in
          the stream.</para>

        <para>Another common use of <command>svnlook</command> is to
          actually view the contents of a revision or transaction
          tree.  Examining the output of <command>svnlook
          tree</command> command, which displays the directories and
          files in the requested tree (optionally showing the
          filesystem node revision IDs for each of those paths) can be
          extremely helpful to administrators deciding on whether or
          not it is safe to remove a seemingly dead transaction.  It
          is also quite useful for Subversion developers who are
          diagnosing filesystem-related problems when they
          arise.</para>

        <screen>
$ svnlook tree path/to/repos --show-ids
/ &lt;0.0.1&gt;
 A/ &lt;2.0.1&gt;
  B/ &lt;4.0.1&gt;
   lambda &lt;5.0.1&gt;
   E/ &lt;6.0.1&gt;
    alpha &lt;7.0.1&gt;
    beta &lt;8.0.1&gt;
   F/ &lt;9.0.1&gt;
  mu &lt;3.0.1&gt;
  C/ &lt;a.0.1&gt;
  D/ &lt;b.0.1&gt;
   gamma &lt;c.0.1&gt;
   G/ &lt;d.0.1&gt;
    pi &lt;e.0.1&gt;
    rho &lt;f.0.1&gt;
    tau &lt;g.0.1&gt;
   H/ &lt;h.0.1&gt;
    chi &lt;i.0.1&gt;
    omega &lt;k.0.1&gt;
    psi &lt;j.0.1&gt;
 iota &lt;1.0.1&gt;
</screen>

        <para><command>svnlook</command> can perform a variety of
          other queries, displaying subsets of bits of information
          we've mentioned previously, reporting which paths were
          modified in a given revision or transaction, showing textual
          and property differences made to files and directories, and
          so on.  The following is a brief description of the current
          list of subcommands accepted by <command>svnlook</command>,
          and the output of those subcommands:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><literal>author</literal></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Print the tree's author.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><literal>date</literal></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Print the tree's datestamp.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><literal>changed</literal></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>List all files and directories that changed in the 
                tree.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          
          <varlistentry>
            <term><literal>diff</literal></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Print unified diffs of changed files.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          
          <varlistentry>
            <term><literal>dirs-changed</literal></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>List the directories that changed in the tree.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><literal>info</literal></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Print the tree's author, datestamp, log message
                character count, and log message.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><literal>log</literal></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Print the tree's log message.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><literal>tree</literal></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Print the tree listing, optionally revealing the
                filesystem node revision IDs associated with each
                path.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><literal>youngest</literal></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Print the youngest revision number.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="svn-ch-5-sect-2.2.2">
        <title>svnadmin</title>

        <para>The <command>svnadmin</command> program is the
          repository administrator's best friend.  Besides providing
          the ability to create Subversion repositories, this program
          allows you perform several maintenance operations on those
          repositories.  The syntax of <command>svnadmin</command> is
          similar to that of <command>svnlook</command>:</para>

        <screen>
$ svnadmin help
general usage: svnadmin SUBCOMMAND REPOS_PATH  [ARGS &amp; OPTIONS ...]
Type "svnadmin help &lt;subcommand&gt;" for help on a specific subcommand.

Available subcommands:
   create
   createtxn
   dump
&hellip;
</screen>

        <para>We've already mentioned <command>svnadmin</command>'s
          <literal>create</literal> subcommand (see <xref
          linkend="svn-ch-5-sect-1"/>).  Most of the others we will
          cover in more detail later in this chapter.  For now, let's
          just take a quick glance at what each of the available
          subcommands offers.</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><literal>create</literal></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Creates a new Subversion repository.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><literal>createtxn</literal></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Creates a transaction in the repository based on a
                given existing revision.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><literal>dump</literal></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Dumps the contents of the repository, bounded by a
                given set of revisions, using a portable dump format.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><literal>load</literal></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Loads a set of revisions into a repository from a
                stream of data that uses the same portable dump format
                generated by the <literal>dump</literal> subcommand.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><literal>lscr</literal></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>List the revisions in which a given path in the
                repository was modified.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><literal>lstxns</literal></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>List the names of uncommitted Subversion
                transactions which currently exist in the repository.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><literal>recover</literal></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Perform recovery steps on a repository that is in
                need of such, generally after a fatal error has
                occurred which prevented a process from cleanly
                shutting down its communication with the repository.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><literal>rmtxns</literal></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Cleanly remove Subversion transactions from the
                repository (conveniently fed by output from the
                <literal>lstxns</literal> subcommand).</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><literal>setlog</literal></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Replace the current value of the
                <literal>svn:log</literal> (commit log message)
                property on a given revision in the repository with a
                new value.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="svn-ch-5-sect-2.2.3">
        <title>svnshell.py</title>

        <para>The Subversion source tree also comes with a shell-like
          interface to the repository.  The
          <command>svnshell.py</command> Python script (located in
          <filename>tools/examples/</filename> in the source tree)
          uses Subversion's language bindings (so you have to have
          those properly compiled and installed in order for this
          script to work) to connect to the repository and filesystem
          libraries.</para>

        <para>Once started, the program behaves similarly to a shell
          program, allowing you to browse the various directories in
          your repository.  Initially, you are
          <quote>positioned</quote> in the root directory of the HEAD
          revision of the repository, and presented with a command
          prompt.  You can use the <literal>help</literal> command at
          any time to display a list of available commands and what
          they do.</para>

        <screen>
$ svnshell.py /path/to/repos
&lt;rev: 2 /&gt;$
 help
Available commands:
  cat FILE     : dump the contents of FILE
  cd DIR       : change the current working directory to DIR
  exit         : exit the shell
  ls [PATH]    : list the contents of the current directory
  lstxns       : list the transactions available for browsing
  setrev REV   : set the current revision to browse
  settxn TXN   : set the current transaction to browse
  youngest     : list the youngest browsable revision number
&lt;rev: 2 /&gt;$
</screen>

        <para>Navigating the directory structure of your repository is
          done in the same way you would navigate a regular Unix or
          Windows shell&mdash;using the <literal>cd</literal> command.
          At all times, the command prompt will show you what revision
          (prefixed by <literal>rev:</literal>) or transaction
          (prefixed by <literal>txn:</literal>) you are currently
          examining, and at what path location in that revision or
          transaction.  You can change your current revision or
          transaction with the <literal>setrev</literal> and
          <literal>settxn</literal> commands, respectively.  As in a
          Unix shell, you can use the <literal>ls</literal> command to
          display the contents of the current directory, and you can
          use the <literal>cat</literal> command to display the
          contents of a file.</para>

        <screen>
&lt;rev: 2 /&gt;$ ls
   REV   AUTHOR  NODE-REV-ID     SIZE         DATE NAME
----------------------------------------------------------------------------
     1    sally &lt;     2.0.1&gt;          Nov 15 11:50 A/
     2    harry &lt;     1.0.2&gt;       56 Nov 19 08:19 iota
&lt;rev: 2 /&gt;$ cd A
&lt;rev: 2 /A&gt;$ ls
   REV   AUTHOR  NODE-REV-ID     SIZE         DATE NAME
----------------------------------------------------------------------------
     1    sally &lt;     4.0.1&gt;          Nov 15 11:50 B/
     1    sally &lt;     a.0.1&gt;          Nov 15 11:50 C/
     1    sally &lt;     b.0.1&gt;          Nov 15 11:50 D/
     1    sally &lt;     3.0.1&gt;       23 Nov 15 11:50 mu
&lt;rev: 2 /A&gt;$ cd D/G 
&lt;rev: 2 /A/D/G&gt;$ ls
   REV   AUTHOR  NODE-REV-ID     SIZE         DATE NAME
----------------------------------------------------------------------------
     1    sally &lt;     e.0.1&gt;       23 Nov 15 11:50 pi
     1    sally &lt;     f.0.1&gt;       24 Nov 15 11:50 rho
     1    sally &lt;     g.0.1&gt;       24 Nov 15 11:50 tau
&lt;rev: 2 /A&gt;$ cd ../..
&lt;rev: 2 /&gt;$ cat iota
This is the file 'iota'.
Added this text in revision 2.

&lt;rev: 2 /&gt;$ setrev 1; cat iota
This is the file 'iota'.

&lt;rev: 1 /&gt;$ exit
$
</screen>

        <para>As you can see in the previous example, multiple
          commands may be specified at a single command prompt,
          separated by a semicolon.  Also, the shell understands the
          notions of relative and absolute paths, and will properly
          handle the <literal>.</literal> and <literal>..</literal>
          special path components.</para>

        <para>The <literal>youngest</literal> command displays the
          youngest revision.  This is useful for determining the range
          of valid revisions you can use as arguments to the
          <literal>setrev</literal> command&mdash;you are allowed to
          browse all the revisions (recalling that they are named with
          integers) between 0 and the youngest, inclusively.
          Determining the valid browsable transactions isn't quite as
          pretty.  Use the <command>lstxns</command> command to list
          the transactions that you are able to browse.  The list of
          browsable transactions is the same list that
          <command>svnadmin lstxns</command> returns, and the same
          list that is valid for use with <command>svnlook</command>'s
          <option>--transaction</option> option.</para>

        <para>Once you've finished using the shell, you can exit
          cleanly by using the <command>exit</command> command.
          Alternatively, you can supply an end-of-file
          character&mdash;Control-D (though some Win32 Python
          distributions use the Windows Control-Z convention
          instead).</para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="svn-ch-5-sect-2.2.4">
        <title>Berkeley DB Utilities</title>

        <para>Currently, the Subversion repository has only one
          database back-end&mdash;Berkeley DB.  All of your filesystem's
          structure and data live in a set of tables within the
          <filename>db</filename> subdirectory of your repository.
          This subdirectory is a regular Berkeley DB environment
          directory, and can therefore be used in conjunction with any
          of Berkeley's database tools (you can see the documentation
          for these tools at SleepyCat's website, <systemitem
          class="url">http://www.sleepycat.com/</systemitem>).  For
          day-to-day Subversion use, these tools are unnecessary,
          however, they do provide some important functionality that
          is currently not provided by Subversion itself.</para>
  
        <para>For example, because Subversion uses Berkeley DB's
          logging facilities, the database first writes out a
          description of any modifications it is about to make, and
          then makes the modification itself.  This is to ensure that
          if something goes wrong, the database system can back up to
          a previous <firstterm>checkpoint</firstterm>&mdash;a
          location in the log files known not to be corrupt&mdash;and
          replay transactions until the data is restored to a usable
          state.  This functionality is one of the main reasons why
          Berkeley DB was chosen as Subversion's initial database
          back-end.</para>

        <para>Over time, these log files can accumulate in mass
          quantities.  That is by design, of course.  You should be
          able to recreate your entire database using nothing but the
          log files, so these files are important for catastrophic
          database recovery.  But typically, you'll want to archive
          the log files that are no longer in use by Berkeley DB, and
          then remove them from disk to conserve space.  Berkeley DB
          provides a <command>db_archive</command> utility for, among
          other things, listing the log files that are associated with
          a given database and which are no longer in use.  That way,
          you know which files to archive and remove.</para>

        <para>Subversion's own repository uses a
          <literal>post-commit</literal> hook script, which, after
          performing a <quote>hot backup</quote> of the repository,
          removes these excess logfiles.  In the Subversion source
          tree, the script
          <filename>tools/backup/hot-backup.py</filename> illustrates
          the safe way to perform a backup of a Berkeley DB database
          environment while it's being actively accessed:  recursively
          copy the entire repository directory, then re-copy the
          logfiles listed by <command>db_archive -l</command>.</para>
            
        <para>Generally speaking, only the truly paranoid would need
          to backup their entire repository every time a commit
          occurred.  Subversion's repository is truly paranoid for what
          should be obvious reasons!  However, assuming that a given
          repository has some other redundancy mechanism in place with
          relatively fine granularity (per-commit, for example), a hot
          backup of the database might be something that a repository
          administrator would want to include as part of a system-wide
          nightly backup.  For more repositories, archived commit
          emails alone are sufficient restoration sources, at least
          for the last few commits.  But it's your data; protect it as
          much as you'd like.</para>
            
        <para>Berkeley DB also comes with a pair of utilities for
          converting the database tables into flat ASCII text files,
          suitable for transferring from machine to machine,
          irrespective of architecture or operating system.  The
          <command>db_dump</command> and <command>db_load</command>
          programs write and read, respectively, a custom file format
          which describes the keys and values in a Berkeley DB
          database.</para>            
        
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <!-- ***************************************************************** -->
    <sect2 id="svn-ch-5-sect-2.3">
      <title>Repository Cleanup</title>
            
      <para>Your Subversion repository will generally require very
        little attention once it is configured to your liking.
        However, there are times when some manual assistance from an
        administrator might be in order.  The
        <command>svnadmin</command> utility provides some helpful
        functionality to assist you in performing such tasks as</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>modifying commit log messages,</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>removing dead transactions,</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>recovering <quote>wedged</quote> repositories, and</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>migrating repository contents to a different
            repository.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Perhaps the most commonly used of
        <command>svnadmin</command>'s subcommands is
        <literal>setlog</literal>.  When a transaction is committed to
        the repository and promoted to a revision, the descriptive log
        message associated with that new revision (and provided by the
        user) is stored as an unversioned property attached to the
        revision itself.  In other words, the repository remembers
        only the latest value of the property, and discards previous
        ones.</para>

      <para>Sometimes a user will have an error in her log message (a
        misspelling or some misinformation, perhaps).  If the
        repository is configured (using the
        <literal>pre-revprop-change</literal> and
        <literal>post-revprop-change</literal> hooks; see <xref
        linkend=""/>) to accept changes to this log message after the
        commit is finished, then the user can <quote>fix</quote> her
        log message remotely using the <command>svn</command> client
        program.  However, because of the potential to lose
        information forever, Subversion repositories are not, by
        default, configured to allow changes to unversioned properties&mdash;
        except by an administrator.</para>

      <para>If a log message needs to be changed by an administrator,
        this can be done using <command>svnadmin setlog</command>.
        This command changes the log message (the
        <literal>svn:log</literal> property) on a given revision of a
        repository, reading the new value from a provided file.</para>
          
      <screen>
$ echo "Here is the new, correct log message" > newlog.txt
$ svnadmin setlog myrepos newlog.txt -r 388
</screen>
      
      <sidebar>
        <title>Don't Lose That Log Message!</title>
        
        <para>Administrators should be aware that using
          <command>svnadmin setlog</command> bypasses any revision
          property hook scripts that might be active for the
          repository.  Be extremely careful with this subcommand,
          ensuring that you are providing the correct revision number
          for the change.</para>
      </sidebar>

      <para>Another common use of <command>svnadmin</command> is to
        query the repository for outstanding&mdash;possibly
        dead&mdash;Subversion transactions.  In the event that commit
        should fail, the transaction is usually cleaned up.  That is,
        the transaction itself is removed from the repository, and any
        data associated with (and only with) that transaction is
        removed as well.  Occasionally, though, a failure occurs in
        such a way that the cleanup of the transaction never happens.
        This could happen for several reasons: perhaps the client
        operation was inelegantly terminated by the user, or a network
        failure might have occurred in the middle of an operation, etc.
        Regardless of the reason, these dead transactions serve only
        to clutter the repository and consume resources.</para>

      <para>You can use <command>svnadmin</command>'s
        <literal>lstxns</literal> command to list the names of the
        currently outstanding transactions.</para>

      <screen>
$ svnadmin lstxns myrepos
19
3a1
a45
$
</screen>

      <para>Each item in the resultant output can then be used with
        <command>svnlook</command> (and its
        <option>--transaction</option> option) to determine who
        created the transaction, when it was created, what types of
        changes were made in the transaction&mdash;in other words,
        whether or not the transaction is a safe candidate for
        removal!  If so, the transaction's name can be passed to
        <command>svnadmin rmtxns</command>, which will perform the
        cleanup of the transaction.  In fact, the
        <literal>rmtxns</literal> subcommand can take its input
        directly from the output of <literal>lstxns</literal>!</para>

      <screen>
$ svnadmin lstxns myrepos | svnadmin rmtxns myrepos
$
</screen>

      <para>Of course, if you use these two subcommands like this, you
        should consider disabling client access to your repository in
        case someone begins a legitimate transaction before you start
        your cleanup.  The following is a little bit of
        shell-scripting that can quickly generate information about
        each outstanding transaction in your repository:</para>

      <example id="svn-ch-5-sect-2.3-ex-1">
        <title>Reporting outstanding transactions</title>

        <programlisting>
#!/bin/sh

### Generate informational output for all outstanding transactions in
### a Subversion repository

SVNADMIN=/usr/local/bin/svnadmin
SVNLOOK=/usr/local/bin/svnlook

REPOS=${1}
if [ x$REPOS = x ] ; then
  echo "usage: $0 REPOS_PATH"
  exit
fi

for TXN in `${SVNADMIN} lstxns ${REPOS}`; do 
  echo "---[ Transaction ${TXN} ]-------------------------------------------"
  ${SVNLOOK} info ${REPOS} --transaction ${TXN}
done
</programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>You can run the previous script using
        <command>/path/to/script /path/to/repos</command>.  The output
        is basically a concatenation of several chunks of
        <command>svnlook info</command> output (see <xref
        linkend="svn-ch-5-sect-2.2.1"/>), and will look something
        like:</para>

      <screen>
$ txn-info.sh myrepos
---[ Transaction 19 ]-------------------------------------------
sally
2001-09-04 11:57:19 -0500 (Tue, 04 Sep 2001)
0
---[ Transaction 3a1 ]-------------------------------------------
harry
2001-09-10 16:50:30 -0500 (Mon, 10 Sep 2001)
39
Trying to commit over a faulty network.
---[ Transaction a45 ]-------------------------------------------
sally
2001-09-12 11:09:28 -0500 (Wed, 12 Sep 2001)
0
$
</screen>

      <para>Usually, if you see a dead transaction that has no log
        message attached to it, this is the result of a failed update
        (or update-like) operation.  These operations use Subversion
        transactions under the hood to mimic working copy state.
        Since they are never intended to be committed, Subversion
        doesn't require a log message for those transactions.
        Transactions that do have log messages attached are almost
        certainly failed commits of some sort.  Also, a transaction's
        datestamp can provide interesting information&mdash;for
        example, how likely is it that an operation begun nine months
        ago is still active?</para>

      <para>In short, transaction cleanup decisions need not be made
        unwisely.  Various sources of information&mdash;including
        Apache's error and access logs, the logs of successful
        Subversion commits, and so on&mdash;can be employed in the
        decision-making process.  Finally, an administrator can often
        simply communicate with a seemingly dead transaction's owner
        (via email, for example) to verify that the transaction is, in
        fact, in a zombie state.</para>

    </sect2>

    <!-- ***************************************************************** -->
    <sect2 id="svn-ch-5-sect-2.4">
      <title>Repository recovery</title>

      <para>In the course of using your Subversion repository, bugs in
        Subversion itself, or certain fatal errors that occur (such as
        running of disk space or available memory) can result in the
        back-end database system getting <quote>wedged</quote>.  When
        this happens, any attempts to access the repository hang
        indefinitely.  Obviously, this isn't a very productive state
        for a repository to be in.</para>

      <para>First, if this happens to your repository, don't panic.
        Subversion's filesystem takes advantage of database
        transactions and checkpoints and pre-write journaling to
        ensure that only the most catastrophic of events
        <footnote>
          <para>e.g.: hard drive + huge electromagnet = disaster</para>
        </footnote>
        can permanently destroy a database environment.  A
        sufficiently paranoid repository administrator will be making
        off-site backups of the repository data in some fashion, but
        don't call the head of IT to line up a tape backup restoration
        just yet.</para>

      <para>Secondly, use the following recipe to attempt to
        <quote>unwedge</quote> your repository:</para>
   
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Make sure that there are no processes accessing (or
            attempting to access) the repository.  For networked
            repositories, this means shutting down the Apache HTTP
            Server, too.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem> 
          <para>Become the user who owns and manages the repository.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Run the command <command>svnadmin recover
            /path/to/repos</command>.  You should see output like
            this:</para>
              
          <screen>
Acquiring exclusive lock on repository db, and running recovery procedures.
Please stand by...
Recovery completed.
The latest repos revision is 19.
</screen>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Restart the Subversion server.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
            
      <para>This procedure succeeds in almost every case of repository
        lock-up.  Make sure that you run this command as the user that
        owns and manages the database, not just as
        <literal>root</literal>.  Part of the recovery process might
        involve recreating from scratch various database files (shared
        memory regions, for example).  Recovering as
        <literal>root</literal> will create those files such that they
        are owned by root, and therefore cannot be accessed correctly
        by regular users.</para>

      <para>If the previous procedure, for some reason, does not
        successfully unwedge your repository, you should do two
        things.  First, move your broken repository out of the way and
        go restore your latest backup of it.  Secondly, send email to
        Subversion developer's list describing your problem, and watch
        how those developers jump on your problems as if you paid
        their salaries!  No greater tragedy exists in the minds of the
        Subversion developers than the permanent loss of user's
        data.</para>

    </sect2>

    <!-- ***************************************************************** -->
    <sect2 id="svn-ch-5-sect-2.5">
      <title>Migrating a repository</title>
    
      <para>A Subversion filesystem has its data spread throughout
        various database tables in a fashion generally understood by
        (and of interest to) only the Subversion developers
        themselves.  However, circumstances may arise that call for
        all, or some subset, of that data to be collected into a
        single, portable, flat file format.  Subversion provides such
        a mechanism, implemented in a pair of
        <command>svnadmin</command> subcommands:
        <literal>dump</literal>, and <literal>load</literal>.</para>

      <para>The most common reason to dump and load a Subversion
        repository is due to changes in Subversion itself.  As
        Subversion matures, there are times when certain changes made
        to the back-end database schema cause Subversion to be
        incompatible with previous versions of the repository.  The
        recommended course of action when you are upgrading across one
        of those compatibility boundaries is a relatively simple
        process:</para>
  
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Using your current version of
            <command>svnadmin</command>, dump your repositories to
            dump files.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Upgrade to the new version of Subversion.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Move your old repositories out of the way, and create
            new empty ones in their place using your new
            <command>svnadmin</command>'s <literal>create</literal>
            command.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Again using your new <command>svnadmin</command>, load
            your dump files into their respective, just-created
            repositories.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Finally, be sure to copy any customizations from your
            old repositories to the new ones, including
            <filename>DB_CONFIG</filename> files and hook scripts.
            You'll want to pay attention to the release notes for the
            new release of Subversion to see if any changes since your
            last upgrade affect those hooks or configuration
            options.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para><command>svnadmin dump</command> will output a range of
        repository revisions that are formatted using Subversion's
        custom filesystem dump format.  The dump format is printed to
        the standard output stream, while informative messages are
        printed to the standard error stream.  This allows you to
        redirect the output stream to a file while watching the status
        output in your terminal window.  For example:</para>

      <screen>
$ svnadmin youngest myrepos
26
$ svnadmin dump myrepos &gt; dumpfile
* Dumped revision 0.
* Dumped revision 1.
* Dumped revision 2.
&hellip;
* Dumped revision 25.
* Dumped revision 26.
</screen>

      <para>At the end of the process, you will have a single file
        (<filename>dumpfile</filename> in the previous example) that
        contains all the data stored in your repository in the
        requested range of revisions.</para>

      <para>The other subcommand in the pair, <command>svnadmin
        load</command>, parses the standard input stream as a
        Subversion repository dump file, and effectively replays those
        dumped revisions into the target repository for that
        operation.  It also gives informative feedback, this time
        using the standard output stream.</para>

      <screen>
$ svnadmin load newrepos &lt; dumpfile
&lt;&lt;&lt; Started new txn, based on original revision 1
     * adding path : A ... done.
     * adding path : A/B ... done.
     &hellip;
------- Committed new rev 1 (loaded from original rev 1) &gt;&gt;&gt;

&lt;&lt;&lt; Started new txn, based on original revision 2
     * editing path : A/mu ... done.
     * editing path : A/D/G/rho ... done.

------- Committed new rev 2 (loaded from original rev 2) &gt;&gt;&gt;

&hellip;

&lt;&lt;&lt; Started new txn, based on original revision 25
     * editing path : A/D/gamma ... done.

------- Committed new rev 25 (loaded from original rev 25) &gt;&gt;&gt;

&lt;&lt;&lt; Started new txn, based on original revision 26
     * adding path : A/Z/zeta ... done.
     * editing path : A/mu ... done.

------- Committed new rev 26 (loaded from original rev 26) &gt;&gt;&gt;

</screen>

      <para>Note that because <command>svnadmin</command> uses
        standard input and output streams for the repository dump and
        load process, people who are feeling especially saucy can try
        things like this:</para>
  
      <screen>
$ svnadmin create newrepos
$ svnadmin dump myrepos | svnadmin load newrepos
</screen>

      <para>We mentioned previously that <command>svnadmin
        dump</command> outputs a range of revisions.  Use the
        <option>--revision</option> option to specify a single
        revision to dump, or a range of revisions.  If you omit this
        option, all the existing repository revisions will be
        dumped.</para>

      <screen>
$ svnadmin dump myrepos --revision 23 > rev-23.dumpfile
$ svnadmin dump myrepos --revision 100:200 > revs-100-200.dumpfile
</screen>

      <para>As Subversion dumps each new revision, it outputs only
        enough information to allow a future loader to re-create that
        revision based on the previous one.  In other words, for any
        given revision in the dump file, only the items that were
        changed in that revision will appear in the dump.  The only
        exception to this rule is the first revision that is dumped
        with the current <command>svnadmin dump</command>
        command.</para>

      <para>By default, Subversion will not express the first dumped
        revision as merely differences to be applied to the previous
        revision.  For one thing, there is no previous revision in the
        dump file!  And secondly, Subversion cannot know the state of
        the repository into which the dump data will be loaded (if it
        ever, in fact, occurs).  To ensure that the output of each
        execution of <command>svnadmin dump</command> is
        self-sufficient, the first dumped revision is by default a
        full representation of every directory, file, and property in
        that revision of the repository.</para>

      <para>However, you can change this default behavior.  If you add
        the <option>--incremental</option> option when you dump your
        repository, <command>svnadmin</command> will compare the first
        dumped revision against the previous revision in the
        repository, the same way it treats every other revision that
        gets dumped.  It will then output the first revision exactly
        as it does the rest of the revisions in the dump
        range&mdash;mentioning only the changes that occurred in that
        revision.  The benefit of this is that you can create several
        small dump files that can be loaded in succession, instead of
        one large one, like so:</para>

      <screen>
$ svnadmin dump myrepos 0 1000 > dumpfile1
$ svnadmin dump myrepos 1001 2000 --incremental > dumpfile2
$ svnadmin dump myrepos 2001 3000 --incremental > dumpfile3
</screen>

      <para>These dump files could be loaded into a new repository with
        the following command sequence:</para>

      <screen>
$ svnadmin load newrepos &lt; dumpfile1
$ svnadmin load newrepos &lt; dumpfile2
$ svnadmin load newrepos &lt; dumpfile3
</screen>

      <para>Another neat trick you can perform with this
        <option>--incremental</option> option involves appending to an
        existing dump file a new range of dumped revisions.  For
        example, you might have a <literal>post-commit</literal> hook
        that simply appends the repository dump of the single revision
        that triggered the hook.  Or you might have a script like the
        following that runs nightly to append dump file data for all
        the revisions that were added to the repository since the last
        time the script ran.</para>

      <example id="svn-ch-5-sect-2.4-ex-1">
        <title>Using incremental repository dumps</title>

        <programlisting>
#!/usr/bin/perl

$repos_path  = '/path/to/repos';
$dumpfile    = '/usr/backup/svn-dumpfile';
$last_dumped = '/var/log/svn-last-dumped';
 
# Figure out the starting revision (0 if we cannot read the last-dumped file,
# else use the revision in that file incremented by 1).
if (open LASTDUMPED, "$last_dumped")
{
    $new_start = &lt;LASTDUMPED&gt;;
    chomp $new_start;
    $new_start++;
    close LASTDUMPED;
}
else
{
    $new_start = 0;
}

# Query the youngest revision in the repos.
$youngest = `svnlook youngest $repos_path`;
chomp $youngest;

# Do the backup.
`svnadmin dump $repos_path $new_start $youngest --incremental >> $dumpfile`;

# Store a new last-dumped revision
open LASTDUMPED, "&gt; $last_dumped" or die;
print LASTDUMPED "$youngest\n";
close LASTDUMPED;

# All done!
</programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>Used like this, <command>svnadmin</command>'s
        <literal>dump</literal> and <literal>load</literal> commands
        can be a valuable means by which to backup changes to your
        repository over time in case of a system crash or some other
        catastrophic event.</para>

      <para>Finally, another possible use of the Subversion repository
        dump file format is conversion from a different storage
        mechanism or version control system altogether.  Because the
        dump file format is, for the most part, human-readable,
        <footnote>
          <para>The Subversion repository dump file format resembles
            an RFC-822 format, the same type of format used for most
            email.</para>
        </footnote>
        it should be relatively easy to describe generic sets of
        changes&mdash;each of which should be treated as a new
        revision&mdash;using this file format.</para>

    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ******************************************************************* -->
  <!-- *** SECTION 3:  NETWORKING A REPOSITORY                         *** -->
  <!-- ******************************************************************* -->
  <sect1 id="svn-ch-5-sect-3">
    <title>Networking a Repository</title>
          
    <para>A Subversion repository is perfectly happy being accessed by
      clients running on the same machine on which the repository
      resides, but most of the time, Subversion's users are not.  The
      typical Subversion setup involves a single server machine being
      accessed from client computers all over the office&mdash;or,
      perhaps, all over the world.  This section describes how to get
      your Subversion repository exposed outside its host machine for
      use by remote clients.</para>
            
    <para>Subversion's primary network server is the Apache HTTP
      Server (<command>httpd</command>), speaking the WebDAV/deltaV
      protocol.  This protocol (an extension to HTTP 1.1; see
      <systemitem class="url">http://www.webdav.org/</systemitem>)
      takes the ubiquitous HTTP protocol that is core of the World
      Wide Web, and adds writing&mdash;specifically, versioned
      writing&mdash;capabilities.  The result is a standardized, robust
      system that is conveniently packaged as part of the Apache 2.0
      software, is supported by numerous pieces of core operating
      system and third-party products, and which doesn't require
      network administrators to open up yet another custom
      port.
      <footnote>
        <para>They hate doing that.  Talk about paranoia and
          insecurity (literally)&hellip;</para>
      </footnote>
    </para>

    <para>Much the following discussion includes references to Apache
      configuration directives.  While some examples are given of the
      use of these directives, describing them in full is outside the
      scope of this chapter.  The Apache team maintains excellent
      documentation, publicly available on their website at
      <systemitem class="url">http://httpd.apache.org</systemitem>.
      For example, a general reference for the configuration
      directives is located at <systemitem
      class="url">http://httpd.apache.org/docs-2.0/mod/directives.html</systemitem>.)</para>
            
    <para>Also, as you make changes to your Apache setup, it is likely
      that somewhere along the way a mistake will be made.  If you are
      not already familiar with Apache's logging subsystem, you should
      become aware of it.  In your <filename>httpd.conf</filename>
      file are directives which specify the on-disk locations of the
      access and error logs generated by Apache (the
      <literal>CustomLog</literal> and <literal>ErrorLog</literal>
      directives, respectively).  Subversion's mod_dav_svn uses
      Apache's error logging interface as well.  You can always browse
      the contents of those files for information that might reveal
      the source of a problem which is not clearly noticeable
      otherwise.</para>

    <!-- ***************************************************************** -->
    <sect2 id="svn-ch-5-sect-3.1">            
      <title>What You Need to Network Your Repository</title>

      <para>To network your repository, you basically need four
        components, available in two packages.  You'll need Apache
        <command>httpd</command> 2.0, the <command>mod_dav</command>
        DAV module that comes with it, Subversion, and the
        <command>mod_dav_svn</command> filesystem provider module
        distributed with Subversion.  Once you have all of those
        components, the process of networking your repository is as
        simple as:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>getting httpd 2.0 up and running with the mod_dav
            module,</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>installing the mod_dav_svn plugin to mod_dav, which
            uses Subversion's libraries to access the repository,
            and</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>configuring your <filename>httpd.conf</filename> file
            to export (or expose) the repository.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
  
      <para>You can accomplish the first two items either by compiling
        <command>httpd</command> and Subversion from source code, or
        by installing pre-built binary packages of them on your
        system.  For the most up-to-date information on how to compile
        Subversion for use with Apache HTTP Server, as well as how to
        compile and configure Apache itself for this purpose, see the
        <filename>INSTALL</filename> file in the top level of the
        Subversion source code tree.</para>

    </sect2>  

    <!-- ***************************************************************** -->
    <sect2 id="svn-ch-5-sect-3.2">            
      <title>Basic Apache Configuration</title>

      <para>Once you have all the necessary components installed on
        your system, all that remains is the configuration of Apache
        via its <filename>httpd.conf</filename> file.  Instruct Apache
        to load the mod_dav_svn module using the
        <literal>LoadModule</literal> directive.  This directive must
        precede any other Subversion-related configuration items.  If
        your Apache was installed using the default layout, your
        <command>mod_dav_svn</command> module should have been
        installed in the <filename>modules</filename> subdirectory of
        the Apache install location (often
        <filename>/usr/local/apache2</filename>).  The
        <literal>LoadModule</literal> directive has a simple syntax,
        mapping a named module to the location of a shared library on
        disk:</para>
  
      <screen>
LoadModule dav_svn_module     modules/mod_dav_svn.so
</screen>

      <para>Note that if <command>mod_dav</command> was compiled as a
        shared object (instead of statically linked, directly to the
        <command>httpd</command> binary), you'll need a similar
        <literal>LoadModule</literal> statement for it, too.</para>
  
      <para>At a later location in your configuration file, you now
        need to tell Apache where you keep your Subversion repository
        (or repositories).  The <literal>Location</literal> directive
        has an XML-like notation, starting with an opening tag, and
        ending with a closing tag, with various other configuration
        directives in the middle.  The purpose of the
        <literal>Location</literal> directive is to instruct Apache to
        do something special when handling requests that are directed
        at a given URL or one of its children.  In the case of
        Subversion, you want Apache to simply hand off support for
        URLs that point at versioned resources to the DAV layer.  You
        can instruct Apache to delegate the handling of all URLs whose
        path portions (the part of the URL that follows the server's
        name and the optional port number) begin with
        <filename>/repos/</filename> to a DAV provider whose
        repository is located at
        <filename>/absolute/path/to/repository</filename> using the
        following <filename>httpd.conf</filename> syntax:</para>
              
      <screen>
&lt;Location /repos&gt;
  DAV svn
  SVNPath /absolute/path/to/repository
&lt;/Location&gt;
</screen>
            
      <para>If you plan to support multiple Subversion repositories
        that will reside in the same parent directory on your local
        disk, you can use an alternative directive, the
        <literal>SVNParentPath</literal> directive, to indicate that
        common parent directory.  For example, if you know you will
        be creating multiple Subversion repositories in a directory
        <filename>/usr/local/svn</filename> that would be accessed via
        URLs like <systemitem
        class="url">http://my.server.com/svn/repos1</systemitem>,
        <systemitem
        class="url">http://my.server.com/svn/repos2</systemitem>, and
        so on, you could use the following
        <filename>httpd.conf</filename> configuration syntax:</para>
            
      <screen>
&lt;Location /svn&gt;
  DAV svn
  SVNParentPath /usr/local/svn
&lt;/Location&gt;
</screen>
            
      <para>Using the previous syntax, Apache will delegate the
        handling of all URLs whose path portions begin with
        <filename>/svn/</filename> to the Subversion DAV provider,
        which will then assume that any items in the directory
        specified by the <literal>SVNParentPath</literal> directive
        are actually Subversion repositories.  This is a particularly
        convenient syntax in that, unlike the use of the
        <filename>SVNPath</filename> directive, you don't have to
        restart Apache in order to create and network new
        repositories.</para>

    </sect2>

    <!-- ***************************************************************** -->
    <sect2 id="svn-ch-5-sect-3.3">            
      <title>Permissions, Authentication, and Authorization</title>
  
      <para>Now, at this stage, you should strongly consider the
        question of permissions.  If you've been running Apache for
        some time now as your regular web server, you probably already
        have a collection of content&mdash;web pages, scripts and
        such.  These items have already been configured with a set of
        permissions that allows them to work with Apache, or more
        appropriately, that allows Apache to work with those files.
        Apache, when used a Subversion server, will also need the
        correct permissions to read and write to your Subversion
        repository.</para>
  
      <para>You will need to determine a permission system setup that
        satisfies Subversion's requirements without messing up any
        previously existing web page or script installations.  This
        might mean changing the permissions on your Subversion
        repository to match those in use by other things the Apache
        serves for you, or it could mean using the
        <literal>User</literal> and <literal>Group</literal>
        directives in <filename>httpd.conf</filename> to specify that
        Apache should run as the user and group that owns your
        Subversion repository.  There is no single correct way to set
        up your permissions, and each administrator will have
        different reasons for doing things a certain way.  Just be
        aware that permission-related problems are perhaps the most
        common oversight when configuring a Subversion repository for
        use with Apache.</para>
  
      <para>And while we are speaking about permissions, we should
        address how the authorization and authentication mechanisms
        provided by Apache fit into the scheme of things.  Unless you
        have some system-wide configuration of these things, the
        Subversion repositories you make available via the
        <filename>Location</filename> directives will be generally
        accessible to everyone.  In other words</para>
              
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>anyone can use their svn client to checkout a working
            copy of a repository URL (or any of its subdirectories),</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>anyone can interactively browse the repository's
            latest revision simply by pointing their web browser to
            the repository URL, and</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>anyone can commit to the repository.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>If you want to restrict either read or write access to a
        repository as a whole, you can use Apache's built-in access
        control features.  The easiest such feature is the Basic
        authentication mechanism, which simply uses a username and
        password to verify that a user is who she says she is.  Apache
        provides an <command>htpasswd</command> utility for managing
        the list of acceptable usernames and passwords, those to whom
        you wish to grant special access to your Subversion
        repository.  Let's grant commit access to Sally and Harry.
        First, we need to add them to the password file.</para>
  
      <screen>
$ ### First time: use -c to create the file
$ htpasswd -c /etc/svn-auth-file harry
New password: 
Re-type new password: 
Adding password for user harry
$ htpasswd /etc/svn-auth-file sally
New password: 
Re-type new password: 
Adding password for user sally
$
</screen>

      <para>Next, you need to add some more
        <filename>httpd.conf</filename> directives inside your
        <literal>Location</literal> block to tell Apache what to do
        with your new password file.  The <literal>AuthType</literal>
        directive specifies the type of authentication system to use.
        In this case, we want to specify the <literal>Basic</literal>
        authentication system.  <literal>AuthName</literal> is an
        arbitrary name that you give for the authentication domain.
        Most browsers will display this name in the pop-up dialog box
        when the browser is querying the user for his name and
        password.  Finally, use the <literal>AuthUserFile</literal>
        directive to specify the location of the password file you
        created using <command>htpasswd</command>.</para>
  
      <para>After adding these three directives, your
        <literal>&lt;Location&gt;</literal> block should look
        something like this:</para>
  
      <screen>
&lt;Location /svn&gt;
  DAV svn
  SVNParentPath /usr/local/svn
  AuthType Basic
  AuthName "Subversion repository"
  AuthUserFile /path/to/users/file
&lt;/Location&gt;
</screen>

      <para>Now, at this stage, if you were to restart Apache, any
        Subversion operations which required authentication would
        harvest a username and password from the Subversion client,
        which would either provide previously cached values for these
        things, or prompt the user for the information.  All that
        remains is to actually tell Apache which operations actually
        require that authentication.</para>

      <para>You can restrict access on all repository operations by
        adding the <literal>Require valid-user</literal> directive to
        your <literal>&lt;Location&gt;</literal> block.  Using our
        previous example, this would mean that only clients that
        claimed to be either <literal>harry</literal> or
        <literal>sally</literal>, and which provided the correct
        password for their username, would be allowed to do anything
        with the Subversion repository.</para>
  
      <para>Sometimes you don't need to run such a tight ship.  The
        repository at <systemitem
        class="url">http://svn.collab.net/repos/svn</systemitem> which
        holds the Subversion source code, for example, allows anyone
        in the world to perform read-only repository tasks (like
        checking out working copies and browsing the repository with a
        web browser), but restricts all write operations to
        authenticated users.  To do this type of selective
        restriction, you can use the <literal>Limit</literal> and
        <literal>LimitExcept</literal> configuration directives.  Like
        the <literal>Location</literal> directive, these blocks have
        starting and ending tags, and you would nest them inside your
        <filename>&lt;Location&gt;</filename> block.</para>

      <para>The parameters present on the <literal>Limit</literal> and
        <literal>LimitExcept</literal> directives are HTTP request
        types that are affected by that block.  For example, if you
        wanted to disallow all access to your repository except the
        currently supported read-only operations, you would use the
        <literal>LimitExcept</literal> directive, passing the
        <literal>GET</literal>, <literal>PROPFIND</literal>,
        <literal>OPTIONS</literal>, and <literal>REPORT</literal>
        request type parameters.  Then the previously mentioned
        <literal>Require valid-user</literal> directive would be
        placed inside the <literal>&lt;LimitExcept&gt;</literal> block
        instead of just inside the <literal>&lt;Location&gt;</literal>
        block.</para>
  
      <screen>
&lt;Location /svn&gt;
  DAV svn
  SVNParentPath /usr/local/svn
  AuthType Basic
  AuthName "Subversion repository"
  AuthUserFile /path/to/users/file
  &lt;LimitExcept GET PROPFIND OPTIONS REPORT&gt;
    Require valid-user
  &lt;/LimitExcept&gt;
&lt;/Location&gt;
</screen>

      <para>These are only a few simple examples.  For more in-depth
        information about Apache access control, take a look at the
        <literal>Security</literal> section of the Apache
        documentation's tutorials collection at <systemitem
        class="url">http://httpd.apache.org/docs-2.0/misc/tutorials.html</systemitem>.</para>
            
    </sect2>

    <!-- ***************************************************************** -->
    <sect2 id="svn-ch-5-sect-3.4">
      <title>Server Names and the COPY Request</title>

      <para>Subversion makes use of the <literal>COPY</literal> request
        type to perform server-side copies of files and directories.
        As part of the sanity checking done by the Apache modules, the
        source of the copy is expected to be located on the same
        machine as the destination of the copy.  To satisfy this
        requirement, you might need to tell mod_dav the name you use
        as the hostname of your server.  Generally, you can use the
        <literal>ServerName</literal> directive in
        <filename>httpd.conf</filename> to accomplish this.</para>

      <screen>
ServerName svn.red-bean.com
</screen>
            
      <para>If you are using Apache's virtual hosting support via the
        <literal>NameVirtualHost</literal> directive, you may need to
        use the <literal>ServerAlias</literal> directive to specify
        additional names that your server is known by.  Again, refer
        to the Apache documentation for full details.</para>

    </sect2> 

    <!-- ***************************************************************** -->
    <sect2 id="svn-ch-5-sect-3.5">
      <title>Miscellaneous Apache Features</title>

      <para>Several of the features already provided by Apache in its
        role as a robust Web server can be leveraged for increased
        functionality or security in Subversion as well.  Subversion
        communicates with Apache using Neon, which is a generic
        HTTP/WebDAV library with support for such mechanisms as SSL
        (the secure socket layer) and Deflate compression (the same
        algorithm used by the <command>gzip</command> and
        <command>PKZIP</command> programs to <quote>shrink</quote>
        files into smaller chunks of data).</para>

      <para>This means that SSL-enabled Subversion clients can access
        SSL-enabled Apache servers and perform all communication using
        an encrypted protocol.  Businesses that need to expose their
        repositories for access outside the company firewall should be
        conscious of the possibility that unauthorized parties could
        be <quote>sniffing</quote> their network traffic.  SSL makes
        that kind of unwanted attention less likely to result in
        sensitive data leaks.  Apache can be configured such that only
        SSL-enabled Subversion clients can communicate with the
        repository.</para>

      <para>Deflate compression places a small burden on the client
        and server to compress and decompress network transmissions as
        a way to minimize the size of the actual transmission.  In
        cases where network bandwidth is in short supply, this kind of
        compression can greatly increase the speed at which
        communications between server and client can be sent.  In
        extreme cases, this minimized network transmission could be
        the difference between an operation timing out or completing
        successfully.</para>

      <para>Less interesting, but equally useful, are other features
        of the Apache and Subversion relationship, such as the ability
        to specify a custom port (instead of the default HTTP port 80)
        or a virtual domain name by which the Subversion repository
        should be accessed, or the ability to access the repository
        through a proxy.  These things are all supported by Neon, so
        Subversion gets that support for free.</para>

    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ******************************************************************* -->
  <!-- *** SECTION 4:  ADDING PROJECTS                                 *** -->
  <!-- ******************************************************************* -->
  <sect1 id="svn-ch-5-sect-4">
    <title>Adding projects</title>

    <para>Once your repository is created and configured, all that
      remains is to begin using it.  If you have a collection of
      existing data that is ready to be placed under version control,
      you will more than likely want to use the <command>svn</command>
      client program's <literal>import</literal> subcommand to
      accomplish that.  Before doing this, though, you should
      carefully consider your long-term plans for the repository.  In
      this section, we will offer some advice on how to plan the
      layout of your repository, and how to get your data arranged in
      that layout.</para>

    <!-- ***************************************************************** -->
    <sect2 id="svn-ch-5-sect-4.1">
      <title>Choosing a Repository Layout</title>

      <para>While Subversion allows you to move around versioned files
        and directories without any loss of information, doing so can
        still disrupt the workflow of those who access the repository
        often and come to expect things to be at certain locations.
        Try to peer into the future a bit; plan ahead before placing
        your data under version control.  By <quote>laying out</quote>
        the contents of your repositories in an effective manner the
        first time, you can prevent a load of future headaches.</para>

      <para>There are a few things to consider when setting up
        Subversion repositories.  Let's assume that as repository
        administrator, you will be responsible for supporting the
        version control system for several projects.  The first
        decision is whether to use a single repository for multiple
        projects, or to give each project its own repository, or some
        compromise of these two.</para>

     <para>There are benefits to using a single repository for
       multiple projects, most obviously the lack of duplicated
       maintenance.  A single repository means that there is one set
       of hook scripts, one thing to routinely backup, one thing to
       dump and load if Subversion releases an incompatible new
       version, and so on.  Also, you can easily move data between
       projects easily, and without losing any historical versioning
       information.</para>

     <para>The downside of using a single repository is that different
       projects may have different commit mailing lists or different
       authentication and authorization requirements.  Also, remember
       that Subversion uses repository-global revision numbers.  Some
       folks don't like the fact that even though no changes have been
       made to their project lately, the youngest revision number for
       the repository keeps climbing because other projects are
       actively adding new revisions.</para>

     <para>A middle-ground approach can be taken, too.  For example,
       projects can be grouped by how well they relate to each other.
       You might have a few repositories with a handful of projects in
       each repository.  That way, projects that are likely to want to
       share data can do so easily, and as new revisions are added to
       the repository, at least the developers know that those new
       revisions are at least remotely related to everyone who uses
       that repository.</para>

     <para>After deciding how to organize your projects with respect
       to repositories, you'll probably want to think about directory
       hierarchies in the repositories themselves.  Because Subversion
       uses regular directory copies for branching and tagging (see
       <xref linkend="svn-ch-4"/>), the Subversion community
       recommends using one of two different approaches here.  Both
       approaches employ the use of directories named
       <filename>trunk</filename>, meaning the directory under which
       the main project development occurs, and
       <filename>branches</filename>, which is a directory in which to
       create various named branches of the main development line.</para>

     <para>The first is to place each project in a subdirectory of the
       root filesystem directory, with <filename>trunk</filename> and
       <filename>branches</filename> directories immediately under
       each project directory, as demonstrated in Figure 5-1.</para>

      <figure id="svn-ch5-sect4.1-dia1">
        <title>One suggested repository layout.</title>
        <graphic fileref="images/ch05dia1.png"/>
      </figure>

     <para>The second is do the reverse&mdash;to have the
       <filename>trunk</filename> and <filename>branches</filename>
       directories immediately in the top level of the filesystem,
       each with subdirectories for all the projects in the
       repository, as demonstrated in Figure 5-2.</para>

      <figure id="svn-ch5-sect4.1-dia2">
        <title>Another suggested repository layout.</title>
        <graphic fileref="images/ch05dia2.png"/>
      </figure>

      <para>Lay out your repository in whatever way you see fit.
        Subversion does not expect or enforce a layout schema&mdash;in
        its eyes, a directory is a directory is a directory.
        Ultimately, you should choose the repository arrangement that
        meets your needs and those of the projects that live
        there.</para>

    </sect2>

    <!-- ***************************************************************** -->
    <sect2 id="svn-ch-5-sect-4.2">
      <title>Creating the Layout, and Importing Initial Data</title>
          
      <para>After deciding how to arrange the projects in your
        repository, you'll probably want to actually populate the
        repository with that layout and with initial project data.
        There are a couple of ways to do this in Subversion.  You
        could use the <command>svn mkdir</command> command (see <xref
        linkend="svn-ch-3-sect-7.6"/>) to create each directory in
        your skeletal repository layout, one-by-one.  A quicker way to
        accomplish the same task is to use the <command>svn
        import</command> command (see <xref
        linkend="svn-ch-3-sect-7.3"/>.  By first creating the layout
        in a temporary location on your drive, you can import the
        whole layout tree into the repository in a single
        commit:</para>
            
      <screen>
$ mkdir tmpdir
$ cd tmpdir
$ mkdir projectA
$ mkdir projectA/trunk
$ mkdir projectA/branches
$ mkdir projectB
$ mkdir projectB/trunk
$ mkdir projectB/branches
&hellip;
$ svn import file:///path/to/repos . --message 'Initial repository layout'
Adding         projectA
Adding         projectA/trunk
Adding         projectA/branches
Adding         projectB
Adding         projectB/trunk
Adding         projectB/branches

Committed revision 1.
$ cd ..
$ rm -rf tmpdir
$
</screen>

      <para>Once you have your skeletal layout in place, you can begin
        importing actual project data into your repository, if any
        such data exists yet.  Once again, there are several ways to
        do this.  You could use the <command>svn import</command>
        command.  You could checkout a working copy from your new
        repository, move and arrange project data inside the working
        copy, and use the <command>svn add</command> and <command>svn
        commit</command> commands.  But once we start talking about
        such things, we're no longer discussing repository
        administration.  If you aren't already familiar with the
        <command>svn</command> client program, see <xref
        linkend="svn-ch-3"/>.</para>

    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>

<!--
local variables: 
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->
