<chapter id="svn-ch-6">
  <title>Server Configuration</title>
  
  <simplesect>
    
    <para>A Subversion repository can be accessed simultaneously by
      clients running on the same machine on which the repository
      resides.  But the typical Subversion setup involves a single
      server machine being accessed from clients on computers all over
      the office&mdash;or, perhaps, all over the world.</para>
    
    <para>This section describes how to get your Subversion repository
      exposed outside its host machine for use by remote clients.  We
      will cover Subversion's currently available server mechanisms,
      discussing the configuration and use of each.  After reading
      this section, you should be able to decide which networking
      setup is right for your needs, and understand how to enable such
      a setup on your host computer.</para>
    
  </simplesect>
  
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ======================== SECTION 1 ============================== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn-ch-6-sect-1">
    
    <title>Which Server Process to Use?</title>
    
    <para>Subversion was designed with an abstract network layer.
      This means that a repository can be programmatically accessed by
      any sort of server process, and the client "repository access"
      API allows programmers to write plugins that speak relevant
      network protocols.  In theory, Subversion can sport an infinite
      number of network implementations.  In practice, there are only
      two servers at the time of writing.</para>
    
    <para>Apache is an extremely popular webserver; using the
      <command>mod_dav_svn</command> module, Apache can access a
      repository and make it available to clients via WebDAV/DeltaV
      protocol, which is an extension of HTTP.  In the other corner is
      <command>svnserve</command>: a small, standalone server
      program that speaks a custom protocol with clients.</para>

    <para>Note that Subversion, as an open-source project, does not
      officially endorse any server as "primary" or "official".
      Neither network implementation is treated as a second-class
      citizen; each server has distinct advantages and disadvantages.
      In fact, these servers can run in parallel, each accessing your
      repositories in its own way, and each without hindering the
      other.  Here's a brief overview and comparsion of of the two
      available Subversion servers&mdash; as an administrator, it's up
      to you to choose whatever works best for you and your
      users.</para>
      

    <table id="svn-ch-06-table-1">
      <title>Network Server Comparison</title>
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Feature</entry>
            <entry>Apache + mod_dav_svn</entry>
            <entry>svnserve</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Authentication options</entry>
            
            <entry>HTTP basic auth, X.509 certificates, LDAP, NTLM, or
              any other mechanism available to Apache httpd</entry>
            
            <entry>CRAM5 or SSH</entry>
          </row>
          
          <row>
            <entry>User account options</entry>
            
            <entry>private 'users' file</entry>
            
            <entry>private 'users' file, or existing system (SSH)
              accounts</entry>
          </row>
          
          <row>
            <entry>Authorization options</entry>
            
            <entry>blanket read/write access, or per-directory access
              control</entry>
            
            <entry>blanket read/write access</entry>
          </row>
          
          <row>
            <entry>Encryption</entry>
            
            <entry>via optional SSL</entry>

            <entry>via SSH only</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Interoperability</entry>
            
            <entry>partially usable by other WebDAV clients</entry>

            <entry>not interoperable</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Web Viewing</entry>
            
            <entry>limited built-in support, or via 3rd-party tools
              such as ViewCVS</entry>

            <entry>via 3rd-party tools such as ViewCVS</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Speed</entry>
            
            <entry>somewhat slower</entry>

            <entry>somewhat faster</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Initial setup</entry>
            
            <entry>somewhat complex</entry>

            <entry>fairly simple</entry>
          </row>

        </tbody>
      </tgroup>      
    </table>
    

  </sect1>

</chapter>

<!--
local variables: 
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->
